<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The application of certain histories concerning ambassadours and their functions, by Francis Thynn, Esquire. Taken out of Sir Robert Cottons library.</title>
            <author>Thynne, Francis, 1545?-1608.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 120 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 107 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94341</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1142</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1403_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3001</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872247</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872247</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169919</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94341)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169919)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 181:E1403[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The application of certain histories concerning ambassadours and their functions, by Francis Thynn, Esquire. Taken out of Sir Robert Cottons library.</title>
                  <author>Thynne, Francis, 1545?-1608.</author>
                  <author>Cotton, Robert, Sir, 1571-1631.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[18], 194, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for J. Crook, and J. Baker, and are to be sold at the sign of the Ship in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: Histories concerning ambassadours.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>A variant of the edition lacking J. Baker's name in imprint.</note>
                  <note>Annotation in Thomason copy: "August. 29".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ambassadors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169919:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE APPLICATION OF CERTAIN HISTORIES CONCERNING AMBASSADOURS And their Functions, Digeſted into ſeverall Chapters, <hi>By</hi> FRANCIS THYNN, <hi>Eſquire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for JOHN CROOK, and are to be ſold at the ſign of the Ship in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1651.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:169919:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169919:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular good Lord, WIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAM Lord COBHAM, Lord Warden of the Cinque-Ports, FRANCIS THYNN wiſheth perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all health, further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of honour, and good ſucceſſe in all his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Attempts.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough my very good Lord, neither according to my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſire, nor your
<pb facs="tcp:169919:3"/>honorable deſert (w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> worthily may chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge from me a farre more dutifull ſervice than my attendance upon you into <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs</hi>) I could not in perſon, as I did in good will, be preſent in the ſame Journey (where I both might have reaped profit, and your Lordſhip been fully aſcertained of my good mind towards you, for that I proteſt
<pb facs="tcp:169919:3"/>unto you remaining in this out-nook of the little world (where <hi>London</hi> newes is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſcant, and the Princes affaires very ſeldome known) I had no intelligence of your ſo honourable place of Embaſſie in this year of Chriſt 1578. untill two daies after your departure. The which bred ſome corſey of a Melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conceipt in me, by
<pb facs="tcp:169919:4"/>reaſon of my fooliſh negligence that would no oftner direct my Letters to crave intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence from <hi>London.</hi> And by reaſon of the unkind forgetfulnes of my kindred &amp; friends remaining there, who would not vouchſafe ſo much courteſie in a matter ſo much deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by me, and of ſo ſmall a trouble to them, as to direct their Letters to me thereof.
<pb facs="tcp:169919:4"/>Wherefore ſorrowing for that which is paſt, that I could not as the reſt of my kindred, &amp; friends did, aſſume ſuch enterprize upon me, and yet not only rejoycing at your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of the good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, of the wiſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch, and of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly behaviour, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with your Lordſhip was received beyond the Seas; but alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous
<pb facs="tcp:169919:5"/>by pen amongſt the reſt of your wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willers at this your happy and deſired re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to congratulate your Lordſhip with the tokens of my old yowed fidelitie, as a ſign of my hidden joy conceived of your ſafe arrival, I have thought it my challenged duty to direct this tedious Diſcourſe unto you, containing aſwell the unfolding of my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb facs="tcp:169919:5"/>griefs, As laying open to your ſight the rejoycing of my well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing heart. And for that other occaſion doth not ſo fitly mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter cauſe to me in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſort to preſent my ſelf unto you than by ſaying ſomewhat w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> may, &amp; doth concerne Embaſſadours; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as wel for that the time is moſt apt for the man to whom I write, having ſupplied
<pb facs="tcp:169919:6"/>ſuch place, &amp; for that it alſo putteth me in mind of your honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable courteous talk which you have often uſed unto me in like matters, I will here in affaires of Embaſſie to an Ambaſſadour pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent my labours, the Ambaſſadours of their abſent Maſter, &amp; make diſcourſe of things belonging to Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. Wherein I will ſhew the original, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges,
<pb facs="tcp:169919:6"/>the Wiſdom, the Valour, the quick wits, &amp; other the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviours of Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, as examples for us in all reſpects to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate: For as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith in his ſixth Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Longum iter eſt per praecepta, breve &amp; efficax per exemplum,</hi> of which kind of people, that is of Ambaſſadours, Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gats, or Deputies, Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of Princes, and of the Orators of Kings (For all theſe ſeverall
<pb facs="tcp:169919:7"/>termes do include one Function exerciſed in divers manners) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there are ſundry ſorts ſomewhat diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from the cuſtome of our age, I will not only intreat as they were in times paſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Romans in the middeſt of their grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt glory; But I wil al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in like order collect, and digeſt the uſage and duty of them as they are now uſed, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:169919:7"/>put in office by Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Kings, and Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, for the executing of their determined pleaſure. In which (my good Lord) if any thing ſhall be found, that for want of more diligent ſearch may ſeem faulty, conſider that <hi>Bernardus non vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det omnia.</hi> Wee are no Gods, wee can ſay no more than reaſonable conjecture or former Authority may lead us unto. But if in the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
<pb facs="tcp:169919:8"/>of the ſame in the apt ſentences, or in the ſweet compoſition of ſtile there appear de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault, impute the ſame to the want of leiſure, and to the rude haſty writing of him, who was never brought up in any Vniverſitie, and I ſeek not <hi>fueum verbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> ſo I may have <hi>ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam veritatem, &amp; mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam ſolidam.</hi> And thus, this far of that; And ſo into my purpoſed matter.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:169919:8"/>
            <head>The Table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>CHAP. 1. fol. 1. <hi>OF the Name, or firſt Invention of Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates, or Ambaſſadours.</hi> fol. 1</item>
               <item>CHAP. 2. <hi>That other Naetions beſides the Romans uſed Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours.</hi> fol. 6</item>
               <item>CHAP. 3. <hi>What perſons are meete to be Ambaſſadours.</hi> fol. 13</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:169919:9"/>
               <item>CHAP. 4. <hi>What Lawes and Privile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges were made and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed for, and to Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours.</hi> fol. 34</item>
               <item>CHAP. 5. <hi>Apothegmes, or Wiſe, and pleaſant Anſwers gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and made by and to Ambaſſadours.</hi> fol. 50</item>
               <item>CHAP. 6. <hi>Of Amdaſſadours that dyed in their Embaſsie.</hi> fol. 73</item>
               <item>CHAP. 7. <hi>Of Ambaſſadours evilly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated in their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſsie.</hi> fol. 82</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:169919:9"/>
               <item>CHAP. 8. <hi>The revengement of Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie uſed to Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours againſt the Law of Nations.</hi> fol. 117</item>
               <item>CHAP. 9. <hi>Of Ambaſſadours evilly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded at their return into their Country.</hi> fol. 130</item>
               <item>CHAP. 10. <hi>Of trayterous Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours towards their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and Princes.</hi> fol. 140</item>
               <item>CHAP. 11. <hi>Of the fooliſh ſayings,
<pb facs="tcp:169919:10"/>and doings of Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours.</hi> fol. 160</item>
               <item>CHAP. 12. <hi>Of Perſons ſent divers times in Embaſsie.</hi> fol. 176</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169919:10"/>
            <head>The Application of certain Hiſtories concerning Ambaſſadors and their Functions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 1. <hi>Of the Name, or firſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of Legates, or Embaſſadours.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE name of Legate is taken divers wayes, being ſomtimes reputed for any kind of Magiſtrate, or for any
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:169919:11"/>perſon that executeth an office for, and under ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, eſpecially in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Countrie than his own, being ſubſtitute in the place of his Superiour. The which perſons ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the ancient Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans did call Legates, the Majeſty of whom the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> preſenting in his Monarchicall Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church doth at this preſent ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, having in every Countrie ſubject to his Dominion, a Legat ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times permanent, and ſometimes temporaneall called <hi>Legates à latere,</hi> as he were his aſſiſting De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putie,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169919:11"/>or his Deputie ſent from his ſide. The Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Legates lay their heads together as Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours, and what ſo was needfull to bee done, it was determined by their Counſell and agreement, and at the length eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by the judgement, and rule of the Legate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> amongſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Nations, is found to have ſupplied the place of a Legate, although he were the greateſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of the warres, ſo much accounted, and in ſuch great honour was this office deemed to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:169919:12"/>
               <p>Wherein as there be many notable things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that which hee hath uttered of Legates (which moſt properly in this place are holden Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties) as are the name of the offices, and officers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Romans, for there were the Lictors, Queſtors, Praetors, Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bune, Conſul, Emperour, and ſuch like, whereof I mean not at this time to intreat as well for avoyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tediouſneſs, as for that they are impertinent to this matter, and for that at ſome other time hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I mean to take fitter time to diſcourſe thereof
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169919:12"/>to your Honour. So now I will only ſay thus much out of him concerning Legates. That he hath not only learnedly (though ſomwhat obſcurely which I could not in better forme reduce into our mother tongue) declared their originall office, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, privilege, and recompenſed honour, But alſo bewrayd the order, and manner of their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, Creation, Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance, Tryumphs, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and eſtimation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Romans, for he ſpeaketh nothing of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nations, whereof I mean here to ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:169919:13"/>
               <head>CHAP. 2. <hi>That other Nations beſides the Romans uſed Embaſſadours.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT was not only a thing peculiar to the <hi>Romans</hi> to obſerve this order in diſplacing, requiring, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to, or procuring the performance of any thing. But the Jewes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the moſt antient and peculiar people of God, with the Egyptians, and Grecians, who were of far more Antiquity than the Romans, are read to have uſed the ſame, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169919:13"/>I mean to produce ſome examples. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the beſt kind of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, or chiefe rule whereby to ſquare our life, either in following <hi>Vertue,</hi> or avoyding the <hi>Vice,</hi> in confirming in Morality, or inſtructing in Philoſophie, is to bee drawn from the examples of others; therefore I will at this time only (ſince leaſure ſerveth not, with more Ample Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and profound Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences to enlarge my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition) ſet down the Confirmation of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall matters belonging to Ambaſſadours by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169919:14"/>with ſhort abridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof drawn out of many Hiſtories, as if I had privately noted them for my ſelfe, ſufficiently confirming whatſoever I ſhall here utter unto your Lordſhip, as requiſite for an Ambaſſadour to doe, to receive, to deliver, and to profeſſe; wherefore in that order I will diſcend to this matter, that other Nations beſides the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans uſed Ambaſſadours by intercourſe to diſpatch the affaires of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries having to deal with other Princes. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (as I ſaid) the Jews were a people moſt anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169919:14"/>I will therefore begin with them, as men from whom all Government and Order, Learning, Moralitie, Philoſophie, and all other notable things have been derived, though ſomewhat alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and corrupted by the evilneſſe of other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſeparating themſelves from the true people of God, and right uſe of his Religion. <hi>Phineas</hi> the Prieſt, the Son of <hi>Eliazer,</hi> with ten Princes of the ten Tribes, was ſent Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour to the Iſraelites beyond <hi>Jordan; Zoroba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel, Annanias,</hi> and <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docheus</hi> were appointed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169919:15"/>Legates of the Jewes, and ſent to <hi>Darius,</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> that they might accuſe the Samaritans hindring the reedifying of the Temple. <hi>Joſephus, lib.</hi> 11. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>Eupolemus</hi> the Sonne of <hi>John,</hi> and <hi>Jaſon</hi> the Son of <hi>Eliazer</hi> were from <hi>Judas Macha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beus</hi> ſent Ambaſſadours to the Romans to joyne friendſhip with them. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chab. cap.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>And likewiſe as the Jews, ſo the Greeks, when come to <hi>Tenedos,</hi> they ſent Meſſengers to the Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jans for the delivery of <hi>Hellen,</hi> which were <hi>Uliſſes,</hi> an eloquent Orator, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:169919:15"/>with Copie of Speech, and Wiſdome, and <hi>Menelaus,</hi> who was briefe, and pithy in Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, that the one by his Eloquence, the other by the force of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, might move the Trojans. In like ſort <hi>Mirſus</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Giges</hi> was ſent by <hi>Oreſtes</hi> the Governour to <hi>Policrates,</hi> the moſt fortunate Prince of the world, and King of the Samnites, to the end that hee might entice and entrap him by his Speech, and hope of gain to bee received, which hee did effect ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly (as teacheth
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169919:16"/>
                  <hi>Heſiod. lib.</hi> 3. by which ſhort notes (it doth ſhortly prove for ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of time) That the Romans, the Jewes, and other Nations had the uſe of Embaſſies, and Embaſſadours; wherefore that being proved, it is now to bee conſidered what perſons are of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie to ſupply ſuch place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:169919:16"/>
               <head>CRAP. 3. <hi>What perſons are meete to be Ambaſſadours.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE perſon who ought to diſpatch theſe things muſt be (as is requiſite in all other cauſes of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) learned, well born, free, no bond-man, of good credit in reſpect of his honeſty, of good eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in reſpect of his calling, that he be no lyar, vaunter, diſſembler, or Traytor; But that he be wiſe, valiant, circumſpect, furniſhed with divers Languages, eloquent, of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169919:17"/>quick capacitie, of ready deliverance, liberall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of perſon, tall of ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and briefly that he be adorned with all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues required, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, in a good man, and unfurniſhed of any vice to blemiſh his cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, or that may win him the Surname of a wicked man. Firſt, that he muſt be learned (beſides many reaſons that may be made for it) theſe examples fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing ſhall manifeſt. In ſo much that it appeareth, that Princes did alwayes chooſe forth the beſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to diſpatch their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires. <hi>Amalarius Fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus,</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:169919:17"/>by Nation a Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, a Monk of <hi>Luxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> a man very elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in the Greek, and Latin, and Archbiſhop of <hi>Trevers</hi> for his learning, was the Legat of <hi>Charles</hi> the great, to <hi>Michael</hi> the Emperour of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> to joyn and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme amitie, and peace with him, in the year of Chriſt 813. So <hi>Jeſſe</hi> a learned Biſhop, for that he had ſingular know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the Greek tongue, was made by <hi>Charles the Great,</hi> Legate to <hi>Irenee</hi> the Empreſſe of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> for to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat of peace. <hi>Amionius;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169919:18"/>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. <hi>de Francis.</hi> The which example, as witneſſeth <hi>Sigebertus, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaius,</hi> King of Scots, imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating, did ſend <hi>Rabanus Maurus</hi> (a Monk of <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi>) Ambaſſador to <hi>Charls</hi> King of <hi>France.</hi> The which matter of their learning, I will knit up with one example more of the King of <hi>Armenia,</hi> who by his Legates offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to marriage his Daughter (being but 12. years old) to <hi>Michael An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dronicus,</hi> the Son of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leologus</hi> the Emperour of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> did for his Ambaſſadours chooſe the moſt learned men of that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:169919:18"/>age, who were called <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thochides, Theodorus,</hi> and <hi>Johannes Glyces,</hi> whereof the one was <hi>Domeſticus,</hi> and the other (as ſaith <hi>Gregorius, lib.</hi> 6.) <hi>Dromo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logotheta,</hi> whom he did not ſo much chooſe to that place, becauſe they had great uſe, and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of things, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they did excell in wiſdome, in plentifull knowledge of Divine and Humane things, and in the underſtanding of the Greek tongue. For they had need to be ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that ſhould ſupply a Legats place in a forraign Nation. Since they ſhould
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:169919:19"/>be inſtructed in many Languages, and ſhould obtain the victory in all kindes of diſputations, as was <hi>Haido,</hi> or <hi>Hatto,</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Baſile,</hi> ſent Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour in 811. by <hi>Charles the Great,</hi> to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> to make peace, who (as <hi>Aventinus, lib.</hi> 4. teſtifieth) wrote the Book intituled <hi>Itinerarium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus having learning, and divers Languages, yet hee is not ſufficient to play the Ambaſſadour, unleſſe he be able in like ſort Rhetorically by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading eloquence, in apt words, ready tongue, ſweet voyce, and ſpeedy
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:169919:19"/>deliverance to diſcharge his Meſſage; For ſuch is the force of words, as it often worketh ſtrange mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles; For beſides that vertue which the <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers,</hi> the <hi>Cabaliſts,</hi> the <hi>Divines,</hi> and the <hi>Magici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> doe place in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing words, we find eloquence to be of ſuch force, that it moveth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible creatures to be reclaimed unto reaſon. And thereupon was <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheus</hi> feigned by his Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick to draw trees, ſtones, mountaines, and wilde beaſts after him, for that by his ſweet words he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced the ſavage people
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:169919:20"/>to civility: the want of which utterance gave <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> occaſion to excuſe himſelfe before God, that he was unapt by reaſon of his ſtammering (which he got, his mouth being burnt by eating hot coals, when he was brought up in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> houſe, where being then but a boy, hee threw down the Crown from <hi>Pharaohs</hi> head, whereby the Divines pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied that hee ſhould deſtroy the King of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi>) to bee Gods Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour to the Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans for the deliverie of the people of Iſrael; Wherefore to him God
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:169919:20"/>choſe <hi>Aaron</hi> as his Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, by his Eloquence to ſupply <hi>Moſes</hi> his default, and to utter whatſoever <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhould give him in command. Such an elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent perſon was alſo <hi>Carneades Cyramus,</hi> whoſe eloquence was ſo great, that hee could eaſily in any matter by the ſtrength of his ſpeech draw any man to his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion. And therefore he (Prince of the Academi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans) with <hi>Diogenes</hi> the Stoick, and <hi>Critolaus</hi> the Peripatetick, being ſent Ambaſſadours to <hi>Rome</hi> from the Athenians, brought his Legatſhip in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:169919:21"/>doubt amongſt the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, <hi>Marcus Cato</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Senate, that they ſhould beware of that man who by his elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, and skill of utte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, could obtain what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he would deſire. <hi>Volater: Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Cap.</hi> 2. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thropo.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quintil. li.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> of whom in like ſort <hi>Quintilian</hi> doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port that in the hearing of <hi>Cato</hi> the Cenſor at <hi>Rome,</hi> he did with no leſſe force the day following argue againſt Juſtice than hee had the day before defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gellius, li.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 14. <hi>Crinitus, li.</hi> 22. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>de honeſt. Diſcipl.</hi>
                  </note> His ſingular elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence being alſo remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred by <hi>Gellius,</hi> and <hi>Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitus.</hi> Not unlike to whom
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169919:21"/>was <hi>Cyneas Theſſalus</hi> the hearer of <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> and Legate of <hi>Pirrhus,</hi> who when he was ſent to any City to require Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render thereof, would uſe this ſaying of <hi>Euripides;</hi> That neat, and ſweet words could doe as much as threatning ſwords, of whom <hi>Pirrhus</hi> was wont to ſay, that hee had ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued more Cities by the Orations of <hi>Cyneas,</hi> than by the hands of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; whom (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſaith) the King had in great eſtimation, uſing his help in his chiefeſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires. With no leſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation did <hi>Scopelianus</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:169919:22"/>the Sophiſt obtain the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of his Embaſſie, for whereas <hi>Domitian</hi> the Emperour had made Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, that no Vines ſhould be growing in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> becauſe the plenty thereof, by drunkenneſſe might ſeem to move Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, <hi>Scopelianus</hi> being ſent to <hi>Rome,</hi> did by his eloquence not only bring ſo to paſſe, that they might lawfully plant Vines,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Celius, li.</hi> 20. <hi>cap.</hi> 11.</note> but alſo further obtained that he ſhould be Fyned that would abſtain from the ſetting, and planting of the ſame. In which number of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquent Ambaſſadours;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:169919:22"/>may take his place, <hi>Euſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius Capadox,</hi> the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor of <hi>Aedeſius</hi> in his Country, who was of ſuch profound Eloquence (being the Diſciple of <hi>Jambicns</hi> the Chaldean) as being ſent to <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pinus</hi> King of <hi>Perſia</hi> did there ſo inchaunt the King by his ſpeeches, that caſting away his <hi>Tyara</hi> (which was a kind of Crown or Imperiall Cap foulded with linnen) the King would have changed his garment for the cloke of <hi>Euſtachius,</hi> which the Courtiers did forbid, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he was a Magici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and wrote by a courſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:169919:23"/>of Witcherie, as teacheth <hi>Eunapius.</hi> And ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding this matter, your Lordſhip may eaſily ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hereby how requiſite it is for an Ambaſſadour to be eloquent in Speech, in delivering his Meſſage. But to what uſe ſhall all this ſerve, if he have not joyned with theſe eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and credit, and that he be of good account in his Countrie before he be ſent? For if he be not, both he, and his Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie ſhall bee deſpiſed and neglected. As well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in this one Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie done in our time. And becauſe I will not in this
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:169919:23"/>point be tedious unto your Honour. I will only ſhew you here (omitting which I could cite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſame) one Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie thereof, for a ſmall thing can give light to a wiſe man, and your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip by this one example ſhall learne that others have told in many. Which Hiſtory is thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When in the year of our Lord (as telleth</hi> Paulus Jovius) Charles the fifth,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Paulus Jovius, lib.</hi> 28.</note> 
                  <hi>the Emperour (by Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracie made with</hi> Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>the ſeventh Biſhop of</hi> Rome <hi>againſt the Floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, attempting to reduce thoſe of the houſe of</hi> Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:169919:24"/>
                  <hi>into their Countrie) did with continuall Siege oppreſſe the City of</hi> Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence <hi>(ſuch was the obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacie of the Citizens fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring the popular go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment) that great cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty was ſhewed to them, who did freely, and truly ſay, that Peace was to bee embraced: But at the length by</hi> Philip Meliores, <hi>an honeſt young man in the Common-wealth, preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing often to the Senate, and perſwading to embrace Peace, he Fathers decreed that Ambaſſadours ſhould be diſpatched to the Pope: yet ſuch was the malignity of the hinderers, that not
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:169919:24"/>they whom the waightineſs of the cauſe did require, but men otherwiſe of ſmall credit, and common Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens were ſent forth. Of whom one</hi> Aloyſius Sode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinus <hi>(who had not done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing worthy any grave affaires in ordering any matter, other than that hee was called a good houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper) was one and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was</hi> Anderolus Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colinus, <hi>rather a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and diligent Merchant, than a Senator, and the third was</hi> Robertus Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius, <hi>whom by reaſon of his late neer allyance with</hi> Thomas Soderyne, <hi>who ſtill laboured againſt this
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:169919:25"/>Peace, made the Embaſſie to be the more ſuſpected. Theſe men when they were arrived at</hi> Bononia, <hi>the Pope (for that they were not of ſufficient honour, and for that ſufficiencie of induſtrie, ſinceritie of mind and faith was not found in them) did ſo contemn them, that hee greatly laughed to ſee, that in place of worthy Senators, they had out of</hi> Florence <hi>ſent Merchants, and thoſe not of the beſt ſort. And that which did moſt ſound in derogation of their Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was, for that the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Cuſtomes in</hi> Bononia <hi>had found in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:169919:25"/>their Coffers for Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize ſake great ſtore of gold thred to make and weave cloth-of-gold; the which they then brought to avoyd further charge of carriage for the ſame; which fooliſh ſubtilty in ſo grave a matter, wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped about with the filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of gain, was the more to be jeſted at, Becauſe when they had delivered their Meſſage, they had brought no further autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to confirm the Peace. Wherefore</hi> Clement, <hi>and</hi> Caeſar <hi>alſo, ſcorning them, and ſtomacking the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe and unskill of the Merchants, did ſo upbraid
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:169919:26"/>them, that their pertinacie ſeemed next unto mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and they with open ſhame rejected, were ſent home,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Thus far <hi>Jovius</hi> tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated in Engliſh. In which is to be ſeen, that the baſeneſſe, fooliſhneſſe, Covetouſneſſe, and want of experience, was the cauſe that theſe Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours were not only diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, and their Petition rejected, but that the poor Florentines were ſtil oppreſſed with the ſaid warre. And thus much hitherto, that an Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour ſhould be learned, eloquent, and of good cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:169919:26"/>
               <p>Now for the other matters, as that they muſt be wiſe, and expert, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> you ſhall find plentifull examples thereof under the title of Ambaſſadours praiſed for the wiſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch, and worthy doing of their Legation, and under the title of <hi>Apoph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thegmes,</hi> and wiſe anſwers of Legates; wherefore I here ſtrain my quill to other matters belonging to them, as followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:169919:27"/>
               <head>CHAP. 4. <hi>What Lawes, and privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges were made, and allowed for and to Ambaſſadours.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALthough this matter may beſt by a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilian be diſcuſſed, for that the ſame is moſt plentifully known unto them, and is a thing that I cannot well intreat of, for that I have not acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my ſelfe with <hi>Juſtini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> Writings, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees: yet ſo far-forth, as either in Hiſtory, or other Authoritie, I have read, or collected any thing
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:169919:27"/>thereof, I ſhall not refuſe to ſay what I can, though not ſo much as I would, though not ſo much as the matter could bear, and though not ſo much as your Lordſhip might learn from others to your contentment, and my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire; And therefore to ſay what I can, I affirm, That it is but reaſon (ſince Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours endanger their perſons, conſume their ſubſtance, travell their wits, toyle their bodyes, ſerve their Countrie, and uphold their Prince) that they ſhould be Franchiſed with ſuch liberties, as both might be ſafety for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:169919:28"/>and guerdon for their deſerts; or elſe who would willingly diſcharge that thing, the perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance whereof ſhall not ſo much as defend his life? But to leave proofes of reaſon, wee will deſcend to the writings of others who have treated thereof. And firſt for the order how Ambaſſadours were received and uſed, <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander ab Alexandro</hi> thus writeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Apud Graecos niſi prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conibus adhibitis,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Alex. ab Alex. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</note> Legatos minimè hoſtium fines in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredi docebat; neque Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gationis munere fungi quenquam, niſi prius infuſa
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:169919:28"/>aqua ab eiſdem manus abluiſſent, Jovi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis poculis propinaſsent. Hi tamen Legati qui cum pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triis ſacris, Olympum aut Pythiam miſsi erant, ſacri: qui vero foed ra percutie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant quaſi pacis arbitri, &amp; Interpretos <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> dicti ſunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which <hi>Alexander</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpeaking of the time when Ambaſſadors ſhould be received amongſt the Romans, and in what lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage the Legates ſhould ſpeak, ſaith in this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Neque illud praetereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum,</hi> &amp;c.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Alex. ab. Alex. li.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Neither is it to be overpaſſed, that it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:169919:29"/>that to Legates, and forraign Nations, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into the Senate, the Roman Confulls were not accuſtomed to give any anſwers, but only in Latin, who being admitted after the manner of the Fathers, the Senate gave them pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of that they would have; but the Greeks (by their Deputies appointed) did declare their minds, if any body required any thing, as the</hi> Atrebates, <hi>and</hi> Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces <hi>did aſſemble their Councells by the ſound of Trumpets. But if they would ſpeak any thing in their own Language to thoſe (being admitted in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:169919:29"/>the Senate) were Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters given, by whom they did propound what was needfull, and receive the agreement, and anſwers of the Senate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And although <hi>Molo</hi> the Rhetorician is firſt ſaid to have declamed in Greek in the Senate; yet ſo much did <hi>Tiberius</hi> hate the Greek tongue, that endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to ſpeak (I well know not what in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate) in Greek, hee firſt craved pardon therefore.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And</hi> Claudius Caeſar <hi>did raſe out of the Table of the Judges, and ſent away the Governuur of a Province in Greece, for that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:169919:30"/>hee was ignorant in the Latin tongue. Further, this cuſtome grew in force amongſt the Romans, that in the month of</hi> February, <hi>ſtiled the Calends of</hi> March <hi>(by Conſuls appointed therefore) the Senate did daily apply themſelves to hear the requeſts of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours, and complaints of their fellowes, leſt they ſhould be deceived in the end by long delay, and tedious expectation.</hi> Thus far he.</p>
               <p>In which is worthily to be noted, that the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans with great reaſon did uſe to give anſwers to Legates in their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:169919:30"/>tongue, which was the Latine, and that hee which ſpake in the Senate ſhould have the Latine tongue. The which ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation if it were at this day uſed, it would judge moſt allowable, that what Prince ſoever ſhould by his Ambaſſadours requeſt any thing of us, ſhould uſe our tongue, they ſtanding in need of us. And ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe when we are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of them things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for us, wee to uſe their language, becauſe the truth of the matter ſhould better be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood thereby than other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, upon the ambiguitie
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:169919:31"/>of the word (not known of the Ambaſſadour ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of our tongue) might great contention riſe. As did to <hi>Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick.</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> in Sentence given againſt him by <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, in the Dutch tongue, where <hi>Frederick</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding one word to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie abſolution and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of life, was by the ſame word condemned to death, that word having double ſignification.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>M.. Ae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>odius Titus liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius, Des.</hi> 4. <hi>li.</hi> 8. <hi>Theatrum vitae hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manae. V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 14. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 5.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Now what Privileges and Immunities are fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to them belonging, <hi>Marcus Popilius Lenas</hi> being diſpatched Legate
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:169919:31"/>unto <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes</hi> (who had beſieged King <hi>Ptolomy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Valer. Max. li.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 6.</note> friend to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans) to will him that hee ſhould abſtain from moleſting the Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the people of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Livius, lib.</hi> 45. <hi>Valer. Max. Plinius.</hi>
                  </note> did compaſſe about <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus</hi> (deferring anſwer) with a circle which hee made with a wand, charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Anti chus</hi> not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of the ſame, till ſuch time as he had deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered an abſolute anſwer, the which <hi>Antiochus</hi> fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing leſt of his war where he doth by manifeſt error place <hi>C. Octavus</hi> for <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nicholaus Damaſtenus</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:169919:32"/>being ſent of <hi>Herod,</hi> King of the Jewes (whoſe deeds he wrote with more flattery than troth) Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour to <hi>Rome,</hi> to <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus,</hi> did pacifie the Emperour offended with <hi>Herod</hi> for warres made againſt the Arabians;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joſeph. li.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 17</note> And ſo wrought that <hi>Syllius</hi> the Legate of the Arabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans was condemned. <hi>Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petus</hi> the Roman was ſent of <hi>Theodorus</hi> king of the Goths to <hi>Juſtinian</hi> the Emperour to excuſe the death of <hi>Amalaſuenta,</hi> where the Emperour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pacified, and hee at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted by the Emperour to follow the Hereſie of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:169919:32"/>
                  <hi>Eutiches,</hi> by his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant denying thereof ſo wrought, that in th'end he enforced the Emperour to return to a ſound opinion of Catholique Religion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Francis Dandalus</hi> the Venetian Orator,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Volater<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. li.</hi> 12. <hi>Anthrop.</hi>
                  </note> being ſent into <hi>France,</hi> to <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> the Pope to pacifie him, for that hee was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended with the States of <hi>Venice</hi> for the receiving of <hi>Feraria,</hi> when he had divers times uſed many perſwaſions, and yet could not remove the anger of the high Biſhop, falling groveling upon his hands and feet (of his voluntary motion, not by compulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:169919:33"/>as ſome affirm) with a Chain about his neck, in the manner of a Dog, did proſtrate himſelfe at the feet of the Biſhop then at Dinner; At which ſtrange ſight the Pope being aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ignatius, li.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</note> received him into his favour, and forgave the injurie of the Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laurence Medices,</hi> Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour of the Floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, ſent to <hi>Naples</hi> to King <hi>Ferdinando,</hi> when one of the Kings horles was brought forth on which <hi>Laurence</hi> ſhould ride together with the King (who came to meet him, not as a private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon)
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:169919:33"/>into the Caſtle, ſaid, hee ſhould then need a horſe, and not before, when hee had obtained Peace of ſuch a King, whereby hee might with quick ſpeed carry ſuch meſſage to his City, whoſe hope in this was not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, for <hi>Ferdinand</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing allured with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticement of his Speech, &amp; courteſie (which plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeemed to repreſent a kingly Majeſtie) did ſo bind him unto him, that of a bitter enemy he made him a dear friend to his Country, in ſuch ſort, that he which made the warre by the malice of this
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:169919:34"/>
                  <hi>Laurence</hi> to the Floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, did alſo leave off the ſame by the words of the ſame perſon. <hi>Brutus, hiſt. Flor. li.</hi> 7. When <hi>Clement</hi> the ſeventh Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, the Emperour, had met at <hi>Bononia</hi> about di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers affaires, <hi>Francis Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vares</hi> the Legate of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide,</hi> commonly called <hi>Preſto John,</hi> was King of the <hi>Abiſsine</hi> Aethiopians (which doe poſſeſſe the middle part of <hi>Affrica</hi>) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come to <hi>Bononia</hi> by the conduct of the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours of <hi>John</hi> King of <hi>Portugal</hi> did in the Senate, in the name of his
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:169919:34"/>King, promiſe faith and obedience to <hi>Clement,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Polidor. de Jnven. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>M.</hi> 2.</note> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> in the year of our Lord 1533. in the moneth of <hi>February.</hi> And ſo with theſe exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples I conclude this title, of ſuch perſons as have been commended for the wiſe diſpatch of their Embaſſie. After which I mean with like examples more plentifully to utter many wiſe Anſwers gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and made by, and to the Legates of other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, in which their wit, and learning was notably declared.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:169919:35"/>
               <head>CHAP. 5. <hi>Apophthegmes, or wiſe, and pleaſant Anſwers given, and made by, and to Ambaſſadours.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DArius</hi> the King en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into <hi>Scythia,</hi> was driven to great need, and povertie; Whereupon the Scythians ſent Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates unto him with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, which were, a Bird, a Mouſe, a Frog, and five Arrowes, which <hi>Darius</hi> interpreted after his mind, that thereby they did yield themſelves, and the Countrey; By the Mouſe, underſtanding the Land;
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:169919:35"/>by the Frog, the Waters; by the Bird, their Horſes; and by the Arrows, their Bodyes. But <hi>Gobrias</hi> did conjecture, that theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents did ſpeak to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry effect.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bruſomius, li.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 30.</note> That unleſſe the Perſians did flie away as Birds, hide themſelves in the Earth like Miſe, leap into the water like Frogs, they ſhould be killed with thoſe Arrows.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Polycartidas</hi> an Orator, being ſent with others to certain Dukes, when it was demanded of them, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming was pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, or publick, anſwered, That if they obtained the effect of their Meſſage,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:169919:36"/>they came publickly, if not, privately; which Speech did ſingularly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt his good mind to his Countrie;
<note place="margin">Plutarch in Lacon.</note> For if his Legation ſucceeded to his mind, he would give the glory to his Countrie, if otherwiſe hee would not have the reproch of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe to pertain to the Common-wealth.</p>
               <p>The Lacedemonians ſending but one Legate to King <hi>Demetrius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bruſ. li.</hi> 2. <hi>Sap.</hi> 1.</note> he great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtomacked the ſame, asking if one man were enough to come to him: Whereunto the Legate anſwered, yea Sir, wee deem it ſufficient to ſend
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:169919:36"/>but one body to one man, which words alſo <hi>Agis</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Achidanus</hi> uſed, being ſent to <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon,</hi> when certain Lacons (a people of <hi>Greece</hi> inhabiting <hi>Sparta</hi>) went Ambaſſadours to the Tyrant <hi>Lygdanus,</hi> who often deferred conference with them, excuſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that hee was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſickly, they willed the Meſſengers to return anſwer,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bruſ. li.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 30.</note> That they gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly came to talk, and not boyſterouſly to wreſtle with the King.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſmenias,</hi> the Theban, and <hi>Pilopidas</hi> who was Victor in <hi>Leuſtrica,</hi> being
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:169919:37"/>ſent Meſſengers to King <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> when they ſhould have worſhipped the King, <hi>Iſmenias</hi> (as it ſeemed) reſuſed to doe it, yet for that he would not by diſobedience utter any folly, he wiſely excuſed it, for being commanded to honour the King, he let fall his Ring at his foot to the ground, which he took up again with a bowed body,
<note place="margin">Plutarch in Artax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erxe.</note> whereby it was judged that he then wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped the King.</p>
               <p>Ambaſſadours being ſent from a beſieged Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to <hi>Alexander Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> then in <hi>India,</hi> did humbly preſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:169919:37"/>to him, much mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling to behold him in Armour, without any kingly pomp. To the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of which Legates (whoſe name was <hi>Acu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phis</hi>) <hi>Alexander</hi> delivered a Cuſhion (brought for himſelfe) which he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Acuphis</hi> to take and ſit down neer unto him, whoſe benignitie, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity <hi>Acuphis</hi> wondring at, and commending, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of him with what conditions hee would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them into his friendſhip. To whom <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> anſwered, With this condition, That I make thee Prince of thy
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:169919:38"/>Country, and that thou ſend me an hundred of the beſt, vertuouſeſt, and chiefeſt men thou haſt; Whereunto <hi>Acuphis</hi> ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſaid; But I ſhall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern better as King, if I ſhould rather ſend thee an hundred of the worſt,
<note place="margin">Plutarch. in Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dro.</note> than the beſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aximines</hi> made Legate to the ſame <hi>Alexander</hi> to pacifie his anger vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently incenſed againſt the <hi>Lampaſcens. Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> as ſoon as hee ſaw him, made oath (thereby to cut off all occaſion of hope of favour) that hee would not condiſcend to any of <hi>Aximines</hi> requeſts,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:169919:38"/>although he was his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; whereto anſwered <hi>Aximines;</hi> Then I require this of thee O King, that thou wilt utterly ſubvert the Countrie of <hi>Aximines</hi> this Maſter; By which wiſe policie <hi>Alexander</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his will did ſpare the <hi>Lampaſcens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Romans diſpatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Ambaſſadours into <hi>Bythinia,</hi> to aſſwage a Domeſticall diſcord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Bruſia</hi> the Father, and <hi>Nicomedes</hi> the Sonne, which Legates were ſuch as one had many ſcarres of wounds in his head, another was diſeaſed in his feet, the third was but
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:169919:39"/>of a ſlender wit, of whom <hi>M. Cato</hi> was wont to jeſt, not unwiſely, that the ſame Embaſſie lacked both head, feet, and heart; <hi>Sab. li.</hi> 9. <hi>en.</hi> 5. <hi>ex Plut. Catone. Cornelius</hi> the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turion, being Legate in the Creation of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſul <hi>Octavius,</hi> ſhewing his Sword in the Court, ſaid, this ſhall perform it if you will not. <hi>Volat. li.</hi> 23.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Genuinus</hi> when he was ſent into <hi>Aſia</hi> to <hi>Antonius Triumvir</hi> (overcome with the love of <hi>Cleopatra</hi>) to move <hi>Antonius</hi> to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour himſelfe to fall into Amitie with <hi>Octavius,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing called to a Banquet by
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:169919:39"/>
                  <hi>Antonius,</hi> and in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of <hi>Cleopatra</hi> being commanded to deliver his Meſſage, ſaid (not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting the greatneſſe of <hi>Antony,</hi> or preſence of <hi>Cleopatra</hi>) the thing that I am enjoyned to tell to thee, is to be intreated with a ſober man, and in another place than where wee now be. But howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver I may ſeem to my ſelfe as a drunken perſon to ſay a thing, yet I affirm, that all things ſhal ſucceed well unto thee, if thou wilt let <hi>Cleopatra</hi> depart into <hi>Egypt,</hi> freely thereby noting the drunkenneſſe of <hi>Antony,</hi> and his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:169919:40"/>love to <hi>Cleopae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra. Plut. in vita Antonii.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When a Sedition was raiſed between the Jewes, and the Greeks dwelling <hi>Alexandria;</hi> three Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates of either part were choſen to be ſent to <hi>Caius</hi> the Emperour. Whereof <hi>Appion,</hi> Prince of the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates for the Alexandri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, laied many faults up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Jewes, one of which was this, that they did not proſecute the Emperour with Divine honour. The chiefe one of the partie of the Jewes was <hi>Philo,</hi> the brother of <hi>Alexandor Alabarcha,</hi> and a skilful Philoſopher,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:169919:40"/>who preparing to plead the cauſe of his Nation, was repulſed of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and commanded to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part; The Emperour ſcarce for anger abſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from doing him inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; wherefore he being thus caſt out with reproch amongſt men, fled to the aſſiſtance of God, and turning to the Jewes his followers ſaid, wee muſt now be of good comfort, for when <hi>Caius</hi> is offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with us, God ſhall work againſt him for us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leo Bizantius,</hi> when he was ſent Ambaſſadour to <hi>Athens,</hi> entring into the Aſſemblie, to pacifie a
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:169919:41"/>long ſedition continuing amongſt them, provoked laughter to the people, for that he appeared ſo fat in body, being furniſhed with a great paunch or belly; but he nothing mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved therewith, yet know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the occaſion of their jeaſting, cryed, Why doe you laugh to ſee me thus groſſe? Aſſure your ſelves, I have a wife farre fatter than my ſelfe, and yet being ſuch, and ſo monſterous, a little bed can hold us being quiet together, but being at ſquare, and variance, the whole houſe is too little; and ſo went on by this
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:169919:41"/>occaſion with his Oration, inducing the people to concord, and quiet. <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſtratus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ambaſſadours being diſpatched to <hi>Pirrhus,</hi> did come to redeem certain priſoners, amongſt the which Legates was <hi>Caius Fabritius,</hi> whoſe fame and name was had in great eſtimation amongſt the Romans, being a vertuous man in peace, and a noble Souldiour in warre, but yet very poor, which <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neas</hi> declared unto the King; Whereupon <hi>Pir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhus</hi> did privately uſe him very courteouſly, conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with him to take re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:169919:42"/>of gold at his hands, not for any evill cauſe, but as he ſaid, as a pledge of friendſhip, and good entertainment; the which <hi>Fabritius</hi> refuſing, ſilence was made thereof for that time. The next day (to the end he might fear <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>britius,</hi> who never before had ſeen an Elephant) <hi>Pirrhus</hi> commanded the great beaſt, as they were in talking, to be brought, and ſet behind a skreen, which was ſo done, then a ſign being given, the skreen was removed, and the Elephant lifting up his noſtrill, did hang it over the head of <hi>Fabritius,</hi>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:169919:42"/>ſounding up a ſharp, and terrible noyſe, whereat <hi>Fabritius,</hi> by little and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle turning back, ſaid to <hi>Pirrhus,</hi> neither thy gold yeſterday, nor thy beaſt to day can move me. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at ſupper, when talk was had of the Greeks, and of the Philoſophers, <hi>Cineas</hi> fell to naming of the Epicures, reciting what they thought of the Gods, and of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, how they placed their chiefeſt feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie in pleaſure, how they avoyded the government of the State as trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and hurtfull to good life, and how the gods
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:169919:43"/>were removed from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warding, from anger, and from care, of, to, and over us, leading an idle life, flowing with all pleaſure. To whom yet thus ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Fabritius</hi> cryed out; O God, be theſe Precepts pleaſant to <hi>Pirrhus,</hi> and the Samnites, whileſt they make warre with us. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the which <hi>Pirrhus</hi> marvelling at the mind, and gravitie of the man, did more earneſtly ſtudie, by breaking off the wars, to joyne friendſhip with the Romans, privately in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viting <hi>Fabritius</hi> (if the Peace were performed) to remain and live with
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:169919:43"/>him, offering that he ſhould enjoy the chiefeſt place amongſt his friends, and Nobles. To whom <hi>Fabritius</hi> is ſaid to have anſwered in his eare. It will not be for thy profit O King, for thoſe that do now worſhip, and follow thee, if they had made tryall of me, would wiſh me king to thee. With which <hi>Pirrhus</hi> was no whit offended, nor took it with a Tyrannicall mind, but did declare to <hi>Fabri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> friends, the noble diſpoſition of the man. To whoſe only credit hee did commit the Captives, with this condition, that
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:169919:44"/>if the Senate did deny Peace after their friends ſaluted, and the <hi>Saturnals</hi> celebrated to the Gods, they ſhould be ſent back to him again, who in like ſort (the Feſtivals ended) according to the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on were returned to <hi>Pir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhus,</hi> of whom as many as remained at home, the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate put to execution. <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar. in Pirrho.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Two Legates (ſaith <hi>Poggius</hi>) being ſent from the Councell of <hi>Conſtance</hi> to <hi>Petrus Deluna,</hi> the falſe Pope, did (amongſt other bitter chidings, and hard ſpeeches, which they uſed together upon the right,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:169919:44"/>and title of Pontificialitie, after that the Pope had ſaid of himſelfe, this is the Arke of <hi>Noah,</hi> mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that all the power of the Apoſtolique See re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained with him) anſwer, there were many beaſts in the Ark of <hi>Noah,</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing therby, that there were many vices in him, the Pope, and many wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men in the Church.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Sfortia</hi> the great, being feared with the weapons, and awaites of <hi>Paulus Urſinus,</hi> had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from <hi>Rome,</hi> and placed his Companie in <hi>Algido,</hi> there came to him from the Pope a Legate
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:169919:45"/>(the Cardinall of St. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell</hi>) being of the familie of <hi>Columna,</hi> and was well received into the Citie. To which Cardinall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt many ſpeeches, when he had ſaid, Shall <hi>Sfortia</hi> fear a Beare (allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Urſinus,</hi> for <hi>Urſus</hi> in Latine, is a Bear in Engliſh) When hee ſhall be in moſt ſafetie under a Pillar (meaning himſelfe diſcended of <hi>Columna,</hi> which in Engliſh ſignifies a Pillar) <hi>Sfortia</hi> ſuddenly anſwered, Shall not I ſeem mad unto thee (O Father) if whilſt in vain I crave aide of a dumb and deaf Pillar, that great
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:169919:45"/>beaſt, fierce with tooth and nayle, making haſt often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times with the pace of a lively man, ſhall not ſeem fearfull unto me? not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſantly noting the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Columnians (who were far off) and lively depainting the wit of <hi>Urſinus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jovius in vita mag. Sfortiae.</note> with his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtrength, which was at hand.</p>
               <p>And ſo my good Lord I knit up this matter with many Ambaſſadours ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, wherein is ſhewed their wit, their govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, their wiſe anſwers, their gravitie, their mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimitie, policie, favour, and many other excellent
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:169919:46"/>things required in an Ambaſſadour. Of which former examples I ſhall not need to make any Comment, or application to your Lordſhip, who by nature have a ready wit to conceive, by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence a ſound judgement to underſtand, and by ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die a heaped knowledge to judge both my intent in writing them, their commendations in ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, and my friend commoditie in reading them. And ſo to other matter concerning Legats to be confirmed by colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted examples found in antient and learned Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:169919:46"/>
               <head>CRAP. 3. <hi>Ambaſſadours that dyed in their Embaſſie.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS you have before heard what good things have been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended in Legates, and Ambaſſadours, how they have been rewarded, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, eſteemed, prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, what privileges, what entertainment, and how many other good things have been belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto them. So ſince there is nothing certain in this world, nothing hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py on every ſide, but that every commoditie brings
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:169919:47"/>its diſcommoditie, theſe men with all theſe good matters are ſubject to as many evils, misfortunes, loſſes, and hinderances, as they ſeem to be adorned with many excellencies. And therefore having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſpoken of the firſt part, I will come to the later part of this Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and lay before your eyes their misfortunes, how ſome have died by the way, ſome have been ſlain, ſome maymed, ſome blinded, and ſome many other wayes miſuſed, as the malice of the doer, or the will of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander gave in charge
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:169919:47"/>for the ſame; And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore firſt to Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours that have been ſlain, and dyed in their Embaſſie.</p>
               <p>The Athenians ſent <hi>Demades</hi> the Orator as Legate to <hi>Antipater</hi> (for that <hi>Demades</hi> ſeemed ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry expert in the Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian affaires) to require of <hi>Antipater,</hi> that as at the beginning he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, ſo he would bring forth his aide out of <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nichia. Antipater</hi> at firſt ſeemed of good diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on towards <hi>Demades,</hi> but after <hi>Perdicea</hi> being dead, and certain of the Kings Letters found amongſt
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:169919:48"/>the Kings writings in with <hi>Demades</hi> did exhort <hi>Perdicea,</hi> that hee ſhould ſpeedily paſſe into <hi>Europe</hi> againſt <hi>Antipater,</hi> the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of <hi>Antipater</hi> was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyened from <hi>Demade,</hi> ſo that hee nouriſhed pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vily cruelty againſt him, Wherfore <hi>Demadess</hi> with his Sonne <hi>Demea,</hi> (who with his Father was alſo Ambaſſadour) urging the performance of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, were both delivered to the Executioner. <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do. li.</hi> 18.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Servius Sulpitius</hi> dying in his Legation, had a Statue erected to him, ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on horſe-back. <hi>Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petus,</hi>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:169919:48"/>the Romane, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you heard, comming to the Emperour to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe the death of <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſuenta</hi> died in his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Porcopius Domatus Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioiolus</hi> (who wrote the Grammar, as I conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture) ſingularly learned in the Greek, and Latine tongue, being Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour from the Florentines to <hi>Lewis</hi> the Eleventh (King of <hi>France</hi>) for to joyn in league againſt <hi>Xiſtus</hi> the Fourth (Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome</hi>) dyed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was departed out of the limits of <hi>Italy.</hi> In recompence whereof his
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:169919:49"/>Children had many privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges granted, and great ſums beſtowed on them, with other money ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates to the beſtowing of his Daughters in Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage. In whoſe place <hi>Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dontanius Veſpatius</hi> was erected, <hi>Brutus li.</hi> 7. <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor. Florenc.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Claudius Marcellus,</hi> one of the three Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours ſent unto <hi>Maſsiniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa</hi> into <hi>Africa</hi> periſhed by ſhipwrack a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the third Punicall warres, <hi>Livi. li.</hi> 50. <hi>Vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Livius, li.</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Julianus Caeſarius</hi> the Cardinall, and Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:169919:49"/>with <hi>Udaliſlaus</hi> King of <hi>Polonia,</hi> ſent by <hi>Eugeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> the Fourth (chief Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop) againſt the Turks, was ſlain <hi>Volat. li.</hi> 22.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Baſsarion</hi> (Cardinall of <hi>Nice,</hi> who wrote the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie of the Greeks in the beginning of the Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Xiſtus</hi>) whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt he went into <hi>France,</hi> to conclude a Peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Lewis</hi> the King of <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Burgondie,</hi> as meaning to ſacrifice that for his laſt offer to God, being ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of th'one part, and returning without doing any notable thing in the cauſe, with very griefe of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:169919:50"/>mind, died at <hi>Ravena</hi> in his journey. <hi>Volat. li.</hi> 2. <hi>Anthrop.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Senate of <hi>Venice</hi> did diſpatch in Legation to the King of <hi>Spain, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mick, Friniſanus,</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony Boldus</hi> to procure (as there was truce taken for a time) a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all amitie between thoſe Kings, and <hi>Charles</hi> the King of <hi>France,</hi> who ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their journey, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony</hi> being a man of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular eloquence, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found judgement, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken with fickneſſe in the way, dyed at <hi>Genua.</hi> In recompence whereof the State and Senate of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice,</hi>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:169919:50"/>gave to his Son <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briel Boldns</hi> ſpirituall li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings at <hi>Patavia,</hi> after confirmed to the ſaid <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briel</hi> by <hi>Alexander</hi> the Pope. <hi>Bemb. li.</hi> 4. <hi>Ven. Hiſtor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus theſe examples ſufficing for the proofe of this matter (although ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other might be vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thereupon, as well out of our Engliſh Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, as out of other Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors) I will now, (ſince every man is ſubject to death, and it forceth not before God, whether hee die an Ambaſſadour or no) ſhew what injuries aſwell in life, as limbe,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:169919:51"/>with other diſorders have been uſed unto Legates, againſt Law, Reaſon, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, Friendſhip and Chriſtianity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 7. <hi>Ambaſſadours evilly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated in their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſsie.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is ſhewed before in the privileges of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours, that their Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitie ſhould be ſuch as they ought not to be tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched for any offence in their Legation, no not for conſpiracie againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prince. Then ſince
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:169919:51"/>this was the Law called <hi>Jus Gentium,</hi> which was (as touching Legates) called <hi>Divinum,</hi> for that commonly they fought to maintain godly Peace. How much are thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Kings, or others, to be blamed, that have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered violence to ſuch men, which of themſelves doe nothing, but execute the commandement of their Superiours? to reſiſt whom is puniſhable, as well before God, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men; Diſobedience being ſuch a vice as God abhorreth, Man puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, Reaſon miſliketh, and Law condemneth.</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:169919:52"/>
               <p>Wherefore as good Princes have been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to their perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all glory, for the liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, good uſing, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment of Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours: So evill Kings to their continuall ſhame are regiſtred in remembrance for abuſing, violating, and offending ſuch perſons. And therefore under this Title, I will ſet down both what Ambaſſadours have been injured, in what ſort it was done, by whom, for what cauſe, and to whoſe deſpight it hath been pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, as followeth.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the Ambaſſadours of <hi>Darius,</hi> requiring in
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:169919:52"/>great words Earth, and Water to be given them, which amongſt the Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, was a token of yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or ſubjection, were ſoon headlong thrown in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Ditches, and ſome into deep Wells, and Dunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>Alexander ab A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandro, li.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Longius</hi> (the Legate of <hi>Trajane</hi> the Emperour) as he was talking, was cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumvented, and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended. <hi>Volat. li.</hi> 23. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throp.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John</hi> the Son of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> being iſſued from the noble houſe of the Romans called <hi>Columna,</hi> (which ancient familie
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:169919:53"/>continueth at this day, of which there did flouriſh two hundred noble perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages) and being Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of St. <hi>Praxedis</hi> was Ambaſſador in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition to <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> which was in the year 1200. where hee did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſuffer Martyrdome, for he was of the barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Enemies included between two poſts readie to be cut in ſunder, unleſs the Divine providence, and his great conſtancie had not moved them to relent. <hi>Volat. li.</hi> 22. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throp.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aurelius Scaurus</hi> (Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate from the Cymbries)
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:169919:53"/>the hoſt being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown was taken, who being called to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell by them, did put them in fear leſt they ſhould paſſe the <hi>Alps,</hi> and goe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Italy,</hi> affirming that the Romans could not be ſubdued, upon which hee was killed by <hi>Belus,</hi> the fierce young King. <hi>Livi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, li.</hi> 67.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Gabinius</hi> the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, after many things proſperouſly done againſt the <hi>Lucans,</hi> and many Towns overthrown, was ſlain at a ſiege. <hi>Livius, li.</hi> 76.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henricus Dandalus</hi> (the Ambaſſadour of the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians)
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:169919:54"/>for that he liberal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uttered certain things, had (againſt the Law of Nations) his eyes plucked out by <hi>Emanuel</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pantaleon,</hi> (the Tyrant of the <hi>Eleans</hi>) did geld certain Legates comming to him, and enforced them to eat their own ſtones. <hi>Heraclides in Politiis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Egyptians joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing battell with <hi>Cambyſes</hi> (King of the Perſians) in the end took their flight without any order, to whom (being withdrawn into <hi>Memphis</hi>) <hi>Cambyſes</hi> ſent an Herald, his Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, being a Perſian, in a
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:169919:54"/>ſhip of <hi>Mitelena.</hi> They when they ſaw the ſhip arrived at <hi>Memphis,</hi> in whole troops comming out of the Citie, broke the ſhip, and tore the men into ſmall pieces, carrying them into the Town. <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodot. li.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond year of the <hi>Peloponeſian</hi> warre, the Lacedemonians experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing all deviſes to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the riches of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> ſent Legates un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> into <hi>Aſia,</hi> which ſhould require aid, and money to the uſe of the warre, and alſo ſhould as they made their paſſage through <hi>Thracia,</hi> attempt
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:169919:55"/>
                  <hi>Sitalces,</hi> whether hee would be withdrawn from the ſocietie of the Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, with which Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours was <hi>Ariſtius Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthius, Trinagoras, To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geates,</hi> and <hi>Pollis Argivus</hi> in his own name going to the King. Theſe repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring into <hi>Aſia,</hi> and paſſing the Sea of Heleſpont, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docus,</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Sital<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> (But, <hi>Herodotus</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth <hi>Sitalces</hi> the Son of <hi>Tereus</hi> Author of this deed) by the perſwaſion of the Legates of <hi>Athens</hi> (by chance being then in <hi>Thracia</hi>) were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown, and ſent bound to <hi>Athens</hi> by <hi>Mymphiodorus
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:169919:55"/>Abderitas.</hi> The Legates thus brought into <hi>Attica,</hi> were by publique Decree ſlain, and caſt into Wells and Ditches, and ſo the Athenians revenged the death of their people, which were taken in the beginning of the warres by the Lacedemonians, and were ſlain, and caſt out unburied. <hi>Sabell. li.</hi> 7. <hi>en</hi> 3. <hi>ex Herodot.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When <hi>Pacorus</hi> the King of the Parthians had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt <hi>Hercames,</hi> to bring the kingdome to <hi>Antigonus</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Ariſtobolus;</hi> Hee perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Hyrcanus,</hi> that he with
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:169919:56"/>
                  <hi>Phaleſus</hi> the eldeſt Son to <hi>Antipater,</hi> and brother to <hi>Herod,</hi> ſhould goe in Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſie to <hi>Barzapharnez,</hi> a noble man of <hi>Parthia,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Galile. Hyrcanus</hi> obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, though <hi>Herod</hi> diſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him from it, and ſo in the end was taken by <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zapharnez,</hi> and delivered to <hi>Antigonus,</hi> who cut off the ears of <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> that hee ſhould thereafter bee unapt for the high Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, upon the which <hi>Phaſaetus</hi> knocking his head againſt a ſtone, was author of his own death. <hi>Joſeph. li.</hi> 14. <hi>cap.</hi> 24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 25. <hi>Antiquitat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Fideni,</hi> being a
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:169919:56"/>Colonie, or people ſprang from <hi>Rome,</hi> did revolt to <hi>Larte Tollinius,</hi> King of Vrentines, by which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion Legates were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched to demand the cauſe of their new deviſe and Counſell, which Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates by the Precept of <hi>Tolunnius</hi> were murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, of which deed, there were which did abſolve the King, for that his Speech was miſunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, the ſame being ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in a fortunate caſt of the Dyce; But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by error, or of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe they were ſlain, it was in queſtion. They that came to the Fidenians
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:169919:57"/>were <hi>Caius Fulcinius, Lul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius, Tullius Sp. Nuntius, &amp;c. Boſcus</hi> to whom after their ſlaughter Images were erected at <hi>Rome. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell. li.</hi> 5. <hi>en.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>The Tarentines by occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſetting upon the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man men of warre carried away the ſame, having killed the Captain of the Fleet, with many other perſons, by reaſon where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Legates were ſent from <hi>Rome</hi> after the manner of the Citie to demand re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of their goods, whom the Tarentines (ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding one miſchief to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) did violate againſt the Law of Nations. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:169919:57"/>being urged of the Romans by warre, (when they found them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves not able to encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Roman force, and would not for their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall pride have the warre diſſolved) they called <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> into <hi>Italy. Sab. li.</hi> 8. <hi>en.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>The Illyrians having gotten a prey upon the Borderers of <hi>Italy,</hi> and robbing their Merchants (being intercepted in the high Sea) great complaint was thereof made to the Senate of <hi>Rome,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they ſent two of the Cornicans (a family of <hi>Rome</hi>) to <hi>Teuca</hi> the Queen
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:169919:58"/>of the Illyrians (who ſucceeded in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, after the death of <hi>Argronus,</hi> her Husband,) at what time ſhe was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieging the Iſle of <hi>Iſſa,</hi> whether the Ambaſſadors came, to whom (uttering the complaint of her ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows) ſhe thus concluded, ſaying, That ſhee would endeavour that no injurie ſhould be publiquely offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Romans, but to prohibit her people, that they ſhould not privatly reap the fruit of the Seas, it was not the manner of Kings, neither would ſhee forbid it. Then one of the Legates (in years young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt)
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:169919:58"/>ſtoutly (but out of time) replyed, Becauſe (ſaid hee) O <hi>Teuca</hi> the Romans by cuſtome doe publiquely revenge pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate injuries, wee will by the aſſiſtance of the Gods endevour, that whether you will or no, this your kingly cuſtome ſhall bee amended. With which bitter anſwer the Queen grew ſo offended (as that Sex is moſt impatient in anger) that neglecting <hi>Jus Gentium,</hi> ſhe ſent out certain which ſet upon the Ambaſſadours departed, and killed the the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, whoſe death being declared, the Romans
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:169919:59"/>raiſed a power, gathered a Navie, and made <hi>Teuca</hi> tributarie with her Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions in the revenge of the Legates death. <hi>Sab. li.</hi> 9. <hi>en.</hi> 4. <hi>Borifrinus. li.</hi> 6. <hi>Decad.</hi> 1. who calleth this Queen by the name of <hi>Teutana.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At the beginning of the Jewes warrs, <hi>Agrippa</hi> the King of the Jewes ſent Ambaſſadours to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious Jewes within <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> ſuch perſons as were beſt known unto the Jewes, which were <hi>Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceus,</hi> and <hi>Phebus,</hi> to move the people to lay down their Armour, and be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to the Romans,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:169919:59"/>but the ſeditious fearing leſt the people would have gon to <hi>Agrippa,</hi> kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Phebus</hi> before ever he ſpake, and <hi>Borceus</hi> being wounded hardly eſcaped. <hi>Joſeph. li.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 24. <hi>de Bello Judaior.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Julianus Apoſtata</hi> (ſo called, for that he denyed the Chriſtian faith, being Emperour) with unſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable furie raging againſt the Chriſtians, contrarie to all Law, and equitie, did not at <hi>Calordan</hi> fear to murder <hi>Manuel Sabel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,</hi> and <hi>Iſmael,</hi> becauſe they were Chriſtians, and ſent Ambaſſadours to him out of <hi>Perſia. Nicephorus, li.</hi> 10. <hi>cap.</hi> 11.</p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:169919:60"/>
               <p>The Catholiques re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining in the Citie of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> conceiving a certain hope of the cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie of <hi>Valence</hi> the Emperour, ſent 80 men of holy orders, as Legates to him lying at <hi>Nichomedia.</hi> The chiefe whereof were <hi>Theodorus, Curbaggus,</hi> and <hi>Thenedenus,</hi> who with the reſt, together with their ſhipps, he commanded to be burned. <hi>Suidas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John</hi> the Scribe, or Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretarie, after the death of <hi>Honorius,</hi> did invade the Empire, and required the dignitie of the Eaſt Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire to be confirmed unto him. But <hi>Theoſodius</hi> caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:169919:60"/>his Legates in priſon, and ſending Captain <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parus</hi> with his hoſt, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the Tyrant, and Created <hi>Valentinian</hi> the Sonne of his Aunt <hi>Placi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi> Emperour of the Weſt. <hi>Paulus Diaconus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Innocentius,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> (being aſcertained of the injuries, wherewith <hi>Iohn Chryſoſtome,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> was troubled beyond all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie, by <hi>Arcadius</hi> the Emperour) diſpatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed certain Ambaſſadours, (whoſe names for brevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie I omit) unto the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> who at their firſt arrivall
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:169919:61"/>into <hi>Greece,</hi> were traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly received of the Tribune, ſuborned there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by <hi>Eudoxia</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, the wife of <hi>Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius,</hi> who charged them with many reports, and ſaid that they came to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb the Orientall Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, Wherefore divers of them being caſt into divers priſons of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> when they could not deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Letters they had unto any others than the Emperour, <hi>Valerius</hi> (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving broken one of his thumbs) did forcibly take from them their Letters, and their money, who
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:169919:61"/>after offering them 3000. peeces of gold did tempt them to follow the part of <hi>Attichus</hi> the uſurped Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> but they pretending that they were admoniſhed in their ſleep, not to conſent ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, did earneſtly require libertie of return, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon being put into an old ſhip which leaked, with many chincks, they were expoſed to the Sea, as to their utter deſtruction, who uſing very dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Navigation, at the length hardly eſcaped in ſafetie, and arrived at <hi>Lampſacum,</hi> there chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged their ſhip, and retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:169919:62"/>into the Weſt. <hi>Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorus, li.</hi> 13. <hi>cap.</hi> 33. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zomenus, li.</hi> 8. <hi>cap. ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hormiſda,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſent <hi>Aemiodius</hi> the Biſhop, with <hi>Fortunatus, Venantius,</hi> and <hi>Vitalis,</hi> Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates to <hi>Anaſtatius</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> to reduce him from He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, but he labouring to deſtroy them, put them in a ſhip without Saile, Maſt, or Oare, where they had been drowned, had they not been ſaved by the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignitie of God, which Emperour willed them to redeliver this Meſſage unto the Pope, That it
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:169919:62"/>was the propertie of an Emperour to command others, and not to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the Popes Preeepts; Wherupon <hi>Hormiſda</hi> did curſe him. <hi>Nauclerus Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lu.</hi> 2. <hi>geno.</hi> 18. <hi>&amp; Henri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Erphordienſis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregorie</hi> the Seventh, otherwiſe called <hi>Hilde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> did caſt into priſon (for the hatred he bore unto <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi>) the Legates of the Emperour <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. ſent to excuſe the four Crimes laid againſt him by the Saxons, who yet thus not contented, did miſerably vex the Legates with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, thirſt, and cold, and
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:169919:63"/>in the end leading them about the Citie, did drive them out of the Town. <hi>Aventium li.</hi> 5. <hi>Annial. Boiors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chilperick</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> when hee had made <hi>Venice</hi> tributarie unto him, the ſame City ſending unto him a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop for an Ambaſſadour upon certain cauſes tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the State, being moved with extreme an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, againſt Law baniſhed the Biſhop, <hi>Aimonius, li.</hi> 3. <hi>de geſtis Francorum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Emanuel,</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of the Greeks (after that he found by report, that the City of <hi>Venice</hi>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:169919:63"/>was grievouſly infected with a plague) he made to be held a brazen table red hot with fire before the eyes of <hi>Henry Dandalus</hi> the Ambaſſador, amongſt others; by which cruell fact he was almoſt blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ever after loſt the force of his ſight, being ſtil purblinde. <hi>Sab. li.</hi> 5. <hi>en.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John</hi> the Cardinall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and ſent by <hi>Alexander</hi> the high Biſhop to <hi>Manuell</hi> (at the requeſt of him, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to reduce the Greeks to the Roman Church) was apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of <hi>Andronicus Corve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> (uſurping the Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:169919:64"/>
                  <hi>Alexius</hi> being killed) and a dog tyed unto him, whoſe taile was thruſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his mouth, &amp; ſo drawn through the Citie, was headlong caſt into a ditch, and then buried.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cuſpinianus Caeſar Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goſſus</hi> of <hi>Genua,</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony Rivico</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> ſent from <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt (King of <hi>France</hi>) Legates to the Emperour of the Turks, when they had ſailed to <hi>Padua,</hi> to goe to <hi>Venice,</hi> were taken of the Spaniards and killed, wherewith the French King being offended, did caſt into priſon in <hi>Lyons</hi> in <hi>France, Gregorie</hi> of
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:169919:64"/>
                  <hi>Auſtria,</hi> the Baſtard of <hi>Maximilian</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and Biſhop of <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentinia,</hi> and was the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion that <hi>Laſeus</hi> the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate of <hi>Ferdinando</hi> was apprehended by <hi>Solymon</hi> the Turk and yet not thus contented, he purſued this injurie with extreme war. <hi>Sleydan. li.</hi> 14. <hi>&amp; Paulus Jovius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Achomates</hi> endevour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by open violence (which he could no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe according to his mind bring to paſſe) to execute the government of the Turks from his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Baiazet;</hi> His father gently ſent Ambaſſadours
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:169919:65"/>to him either to revoke him from his madneſſe, or elſe to bid him war; But how much the more hee did earneſtly (after the repulſe taken) thirſt after the Empire, by ſo much he judged, that he ſhould deale more ſharp, and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly therein; And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded the chiefe of the Legates (moſt boldly threatning extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie unto him) to be ſtrangled in his ſight, and the reſt before the even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to depart the Camp. The which deed did moſt of all exaſperate the cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of <hi>Baiazetes,</hi> and alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate the mind of many
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:169919:65"/>men from him, becauſe that he had cruelly againſt all humanitie, and Law, (without reverence to the perſon, or duty to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) violated the Legates, comming to him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude and end the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie; Wherefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing declared an open ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, his father being dead, he was taken, and ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of <hi>Silinius</hi> his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Sab. li.</hi> 4. <hi>ex Jovio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tomumbeius</hi> the laſt Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan of the Egyptians being drawn out of <hi>Memphis</hi> by <hi>Selymon</hi> Emperour of the Turks, fled into the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt part of <hi>Egypt,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover his force, &amp; power.
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:169919:66"/>
                  <hi>Selinius</hi> ſent unto him noble men, and ſuch as governed the Region, and with them certain Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of great name which ſhould perſwade <hi>Tomum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beius</hi> to lay down his Weapons, and at length to acknowledge the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune of victory, who fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon their faith ſhould promiſe, That if he came in humble ſort, hee ſhould ſtil retain the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome by the humanitie and gift of the Victor, which hee could not any way defend by arms; But if he did proceed to renew the warre, and had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten his imbecilitie (the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:169919:66"/>fortune of Battell being judge) there ſhould there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after be left no place for him, either of life, or dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. Theſe Legates (paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>Nilus;</hi> and comming into <hi>Sarentica</hi>) were killed before they were heard ſpeak, by the mad, and barbarous cruelty of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Mamaluchs, which wicked and arrogant men did think to have done an acceptable deed to <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mumbeius</hi> (looking for no ſuch matter) if (to declare their good wills, &amp; minds abhorring peace) they had opened by that means all the rage, and cruelty of their hearts. But that
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:169919:67"/>deed being ſo proud, and cruell, took away all mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and patience from <hi>Selymon,</hi> who at length ſet an end to the bloody warre, and theſe beaſtly Mamaluchs. <hi>Sab. ſupl. li.</hi> 8. <hi>ex Jovio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With which Hiſtorie I finiſh this Tragicall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of injuries offered to Ambaſſadours, as well of the Clergie, as of Temporal men, by Kings, Emperours, Dukes, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and other perſons, both Ethnicks, Turks, and Chriſtians, againſt Law, and Juſtice, which doth alwayes will that theſe Ambaſſadours ſhould bee
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:169919:67"/>courteouſly uſed. Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to which equity they were moſt cruelly hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; As ſome being burnt, ſome having their eyes pluckt out, ſome blinded by other means, ſome ſlain, ſome maymed in their ears, ſome in their genitalls, ſome ſtrangled, ſome drowned, ſome left to the mercy of the raging Seas, &amp; others oppreſſed with famine, thirſt, and cold. And becauſe it is not reaſon, and Juſtice doth not permit that ſuch cruell deeds ſhould goe unrevenged, as partly is ſhewed in ſome of theſe examples (whereof I
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:169919:68"/>could have produced ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more, but that I would avoid oſtentation of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to have read, and noted many things in travelling Hiſtories) I will in one ſpeciall title for that purpoſe (wherein your Lordſhip may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire more examples of Ambaſſadours diſorderly uſed) lay before your Lordſhips eyes the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge of ſuch deſpight done to forraign Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:169919:68"/>
               <head>CHAP. 8. <hi>The revengement of cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty uſed to Ambaſſodours againſt the Law of Nature.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TOuching this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you heard be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore out of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander ab Alexandro,</hi> how they which offended Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours, were delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the offended, and were ſent for the moſt part to the Countrie of ſuch Legates, there to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive puniſhment accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their deſerts. Here I will collect in examples what revengement, and
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:169919:69"/>other hatred hath been uſed, and exerciſed by open warrs to other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Nations, for inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries done to their Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours: for it is but rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that they who will miſuſe any by wrong a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt right, ſhould with like violence by Juſtice be rightly requited. And thus to the confirmation thereof by examples.</p>
               <p>When under the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of <hi>Magabizis</hi> (whom <hi>Darius</hi> had made ruler of <hi>Helleſpont</hi>) the Thracians were ſubdued of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians; the Perſians ſent Ambaſſadours into <hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia</hi> to require water,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:169919:69"/>and earth, of <hi>Amyntas</hi> the King. <hi>Amyntas</hi> received them with liberall hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talities, and yielding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to <hi>Darius,</hi> at the length, through the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of the Perſians (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their cuſtome) he brought certain Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubines in to the Banquet to the Perſians, whom when the Perſians had handled, and kiſſed, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> the Son of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myntas</hi> taking the ſame in diſdain, ſent his Father to bed, after the which, when free libertie was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Perſians to have carnall company with which of theſe wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:169919:70"/>every one would chooſe, <hi>Alexander</hi> ſent forth thoſe young dames to waſh, and clenſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for more delicacie to content the Perſians, and forthwith brought in neat young men unbeard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, clad in the ſame ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell, and privily wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poned with daggers, with whom as ſoon as the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians began to dallie in amorous ſort, they draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth their weapons killed the Perſians, which ſlaughter <hi>Alexander</hi> did redeem partly for a great ſumme of money, and partly by giving his Siſter <hi>Gygia</hi> in marriage to <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>birus</hi>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:169919:70"/>the Perſian, who was one of the Inquiſitors of the murther. <hi>Herod. li.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>Thirtie Legates of the Cratonians comming to the Siberites were all kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and unburied, caſt before the walls of the Citie, to be devoured of wild beaſts; which deed was the beginning of all thoſe evils to them, which the Oracle did before ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie; For all their noble men (a few dayes being between) did ſeem to ſee the ſame monſtrous act in the ſame manner, for they beheld <hi>Juno</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into the Market<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:169919:71"/>ſpewing forth her choler; In whoſe Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell alſo burſt forth a fountain of blood, and yet with all this did not their arrogancie ceaſe, untill they were wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by the Cratoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. <hi>Athen. li.</hi> 12. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. Which Hiſtorie <hi>Heracli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des Ponticus in libro de Juſtitia,</hi> although in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of matter all one, yet in forme, and names, doth ſeem otherwiſe to repeat.</p>
               <p>King <hi>David</hi> ſent Legates to <hi>Hanno</hi> the Son of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> the King of the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monites to comfort him of the death of his Father,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:169919:71"/>with whom <hi>David</hi> had joyned friendſhip, and they had promiſed it ſhould be confirmed. But <hi>Hanno</hi> taking the Legates as Spies ſhaved halfe of their beards, and curtayl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their garments by the buttocks, did after in that manner ſend them away. With which injurie <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> being offended willed the Legates to remain at <hi>Hiercunt</hi> untill their haire was again grown. And ſending <hi>Joab</hi> with an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie againſt the Ammo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites, hee grievouſly affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted them, and the Syri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans (comming in their aide) with bitter ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:169919:72"/>wherewith the Syri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans being further mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, there were to the number of 40000 Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men killed at <hi>Helam</hi> by <hi>David</hi> himſelfe, and the reſt after were made tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butarie. 2 <hi>Reg. cap.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>The Arabians (having overcome <hi>Herod</hi> the King of the Jewes by ſubtiltie, and <hi>Juda</hi> being miſerably ſhaken with an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake) killed the Legates of the Jewes requiring Peace, but not long after they being again grieved by <hi>Herod</hi> with moſt bitter ſlaughter,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joſeph. ci.</hi> 15. <hi>cap.</hi> 18. <hi>Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat.</hi>
                  </note> and in the end ſubdued, received worthy puniſhment for their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked act.</p>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:169919:72"/>
               <p>Certain perſons of the Families of <hi>Tatius Sabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> (after the manner of theeves, and robbers) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring the fields of the Laurentines, drove the beaſts from thence, and ſpoiled many people, whom they met; Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Romulus</hi> (judging the guiltie worthy to be puniſhed) ſent Legates unto <hi>Tatius</hi> (with whom the favour of his people did more prevaile) than the Law of the Countries, inſomuch that he did not only deny the requeſt of the Meſſengers, but as they were departing, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted them to be viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:169919:73"/>of his people, which puniſhment of the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, <hi>Tatius</hi> procured to himſelf, who a little while after (comming to <hi>Lavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> to the ſolemn Feaſt there holden) was by pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie conſpiracie in an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault made upon him mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerablie ſlain by the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of them who before were violated of the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians. <hi>Theatrum. Vit. hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. vol.</hi> 14. <hi>li.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>The Corinthians being under the government of <hi>Philip</hi> raiſed diſſention a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and bore themſelves ſo proudly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Romans, that certain Corinthians did
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:169919:73"/>preſume to caſt urine and other filth upon the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Ambaſſadour paſſing by the houſes of the ſtreet, for which fact, and other like offences, they received revengement out of hand, for a great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie being ſent thither, <hi>Corinth</hi> was made LEvell with the ground by <hi>Lucius Muminius, Achaius,</hi> and the reſt of the Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, even to the parts of <hi>Macedonia</hi> fell to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man government. <hi>Strabo. li.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>The Legate of the King of <hi>Perſia</hi> ſent to <hi>Aquiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave</hi> to <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, being very hardly
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:169919:74"/>received of the French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, complained to <hi>Charles,</hi> that the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Legates was greater amongſt the Perſians, than the French, upon which to pacifie the Perſian King, to redeem ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurie, as to revenge the fact, <hi>Charles</hi> removed all the Magiſtrates, and Captains of every Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince through which they came, reduced them to a private eſtate, loſing their office; Amerced alſo the Biſhops in a great maſſe of money, and provided that the Legates with all care, dutie, and pietie ſhould be conveyed to
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:169919:74"/>their Countries. And yet deeming this not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, he preſented the King of Perſia with horſes, Spaniſh Mules, and coſtly garments of the German faſhion, and noble doggs to hunt, which Germanie bringeth forth excelling in ſwiftneſſe, and cruelty. <hi>Avent. li.</hi> 4. <hi>Annalium Boiorum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus hitherto of the tragicall murthers fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the injuries offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to Ambaſſadours, which hath been the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of many States, and Conqueſt of many Countries. For no greater villany can be offered to
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:169919:75"/>any abſent, than to miſuſe his preſent Deputie, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting the Majeſtie of his King, and Maſter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 9. <hi>Ambaſſadours evilly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded at their return into their Countries.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AMongſt the other miſchiefs that hang over the heads of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours, beſides their charge, death by the way, miſuſing in their Legati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and bloody warrs that follow thereon; This alſo is not the leaſt evill that accompanieth them, That
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:169919:75"/>at his return into his Countrie (when he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth for great reward, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable title, glorious receiving by the people, and credit with his Prince, in recompence of his toy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led body, his great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences, his endangered life) that hee is not only deceived therein, but in place thereof receiveth either impriſonment, the Princes diſpleaſure, loſſe of life, confiſcation of goods, diſcredit in his Countrie, diſdain of his equalls, rebuke of his Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours, and evill report of his Inferiours, if in diſpatch of his Legation,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:169919:76"/>the event falleth not to his Princes mind, and his Countries benefit; And yet hee doing aſmuch as wit by nature will give him leave, and judgement by experience hath taught him, is rather in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to be pardoned for the overthwart ſucceſſe, than to be puniſhed for thoſe defaults which him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe cannot remedie; God having dealt no more li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally with him in im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting great wit, learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or experience unto him: For in truth if his Legation be not well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, the lack is rather to be imputed to the
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:169919:76"/>Prince, that would not make better choyce, than to the ſubject that of force muſt obey, or elſe runne into further inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of his King, whoſe diſpleaſure (ſaith <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>) is death. But becauſe my intent is not in any of theſe matters fully to ſay my mind, and to utter what reaſons I can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to confirme any ſuch thing depending on the ſhoulders of Legates, but only to warrantize my aſſertion with authoritie of examples; Therefore leaving all other ordinarie proofes, I will deſcend to my former courſe, and
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:169919:77"/>only will with one exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple or two (for that I mean not to be tedious, and intend but to give your Lordſhip a taſte, that many other examples might be vouched there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) diſplay ſufficient au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie in that point, In which Ambaſſadours have been evilly rewarded at their return into their Countrie, as followeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amaſis</hi> the Legate, being ſent of King <hi>Apris,</hi> to thoſe people that were revolted, afterwards be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came King of the Revol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, upon the which there was another Legate called <hi>Paterbenus</hi> ſent to <hi>Amaſis</hi>
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:169919:77"/>who returning without doing any good in the matter, was cruelly hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of King <hi>Apris. Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum. Vol.</hi> 18. <hi>li.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> the Son of <hi>Amyntas,</hi> King of <hi>Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> was (of <hi>Mordonius</hi> whom <hi>Xerxes</hi> had left in <hi>Greece</hi> to ſubdue it) ſent Ambaſſadour to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians, to conclude a Peace between them, but he departed without brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging any thing to ſucceſs, whereupon he was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards forbidden to come to <hi>Athens,</hi> and ſo baniſhed the Town. <hi>Herodot. li.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>In both which examples what cauſe was there, why
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:169919:78"/>either <hi>Paterbenus</hi> of <hi>Apris,</hi> or <hi>Alexander</hi> of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians ſhould bee ſo cruelly handled, doing what in them lay? for when the obſtinacie of the other party with whom they muſt conferre, is ſo much, that neither reaſon can move, eloquence per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade, gentle uſage make willing, or threatnings fear to yield unto their Ambaſſie, what ſhall the poor Legates doe? and if they bring not their meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to effect, they ſhall be ſharply puniſhed at their return, as either faithleſſe to their Maſters, or partiall to the enemie.
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:169919:78"/>For, mee thinks, I hear ſome Sycophant flattering the Prince, and maligning the Ambaſſadour (either before his going for ſome private grudge, or after his departure, for his open honour, in that he is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to his place of Legation) and yet ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his own commoditie thereby doth ſay, that if the matter come not to effect, it is by the negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of the partie Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour, who if hee carry not ſufficient autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to conclude, or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer all things done on the adverſe part, may ſend home for a larger Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:169919:79"/>the which if hee doe not, if thereby hee might have brought it to concluſion, is to be dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med as a trayterous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to his Prince, and Countrie, and therefore at his return to be puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The which thing if he doe (as I would not excuſe it, where open, and not ſurmiſed negligence is found in the cauſe) I ſay he is worthy therefore of double revenge at his home comming, and to receive torment in place of liberalitie, reproach for credit, loſſe of life for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement, and diſ-inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance in recompence of
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:169919:79"/>his deſerved reward. And here ſince now I am fallen into the mention of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous Ambaſſadours, it ſhall not be unfitting in this place to ſhew what perſons, to the ſhame of them, and of their poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, are regiſtred in the everlaſting Records of Trayterous Ambaſſadors towards their Prince and Province.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:169919:80"/>
               <head>CHAP. 10. <hi>Trayterous Ambaſſadours towards their Maſters and Princes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS all injuries which tend to the ſubverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Common-wealth are to bee puniſhed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe not one Citie, but a Province, not a part of the body, but the whole body, not the King alone, but the ſubject is grieved thereby; ſo the ſame wrong (being injuſtice) is not only to be avoyded (by all good men) as chiefe enemy to vertue, but alſo they are to be
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:169919:80"/>hated, and ſharply puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which contrary to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall dutie to the Prince, to equity, to his Countrie, to good diſpoſition to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards himſelfe, to vertue, to good men, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Juſtice, to all men in matter of truſt (wherin all truth is to be uſed) do falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and injuriouſly betray their Children, their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, their Friends, their King, their Countrie. And as in all men ſuch treaſon is to be abhorred, ſo eſpecially in Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, who are the doors, and gates of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, by which Peace, or Warre, quiet,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:169919:81"/>or diſſention, profit, or diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie are brought into the ſame. This vilde fault is moſt abhorred, and worthy to be reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with death, a thing which in all ages, amongſt all men, in all places, and in all matters hath been miſliked, hated, condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and revenged. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no greater injurie can any wayes be offered, than that hee who is in credit, with the life, with the commoditie, with the honour, with the ſtate of his Prince, or Countrie, with the benefit of his friend, or familiar, ſhould under the colour of aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:169919:81"/>dutie, and friendſhip, overthrow ſuch State, or perſon, as giveth ſuch fidelity unto him. But what ſpend I many words to confirm a thing ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly known to be evil? I will not doe it, but by example ſet out ſuch wicked perſons, as have wrought againſt their own head, in ſuch a villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous ſort, as the blott thereof will never be wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped away, which exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples (for he is happy that can beware by the harm of others) I have ſet down as condemning that evill fact in them, and as a warning for others to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:169919:82"/>which may fall into the like inconveniencie, if fear of God, diſcourſe of reaſon, duty to the Prince, love to his Countrie, and fidelity to his friends and Allies, do not reſtrain the evill mind of mens natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall inclination alwayes of it ſelfe by diſpoſition bent to the worſt, and ready to yield to his baſeſt part. The examples be theſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Labienus</hi> the Legate of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> having performed great exploits under <hi>Caeſar,</hi> at the length in the Civill warres trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terouſly fled from <hi>Caeſar,</hi> to <hi>Pompey,</hi> of whom doth <hi>Lucan</hi> write;</p>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:169919:82"/>
               <q>
                  <l>—Dux fortis in armis</l>
                  <l>Caeſareis, Labienus erat,</l>
                  <l>nunc transfuga vilis.</l>
               </q>
               <p>The which Hiſtorie is more to be ſeen at large in <hi>Volater. li.</hi> 16. <hi>Urban. can.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amaſis</hi> (as you heard before) being the Legate of King <hi>Apris,</hi> who ſent him to the Egyptians, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted from him, became moſt traiterouſly King of the Revolters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibancus</hi> falling from the part of <hi>Alexius Angelus</hi> Emperour of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> did defend, and make ſtrong with Caſtles the places adjoyning to
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:169919:83"/>Mount <hi>Hemo,</hi> for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation of which <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bancus</hi> to become again ſubject, the Emperour did ſend an Ambaſſadour Eunuch very familiar un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, which ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke, and renew Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Covenants be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, willing him alſo to put him in mind of the Marriage of his Neece, but this wicked gelding, comming to <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bancus,</hi> did not only not doe any thing belonging to his Meſſage, but with his preſence did rather confirme him in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of his attempt, when he had raſhly ſpew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:169919:83"/>out unto him that the Greeks out of hand would invade him: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore counſelling him, that leaving the champion plains, he ſhould for his and the peoples better ſtrength, and ſafetie, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit himſelfe to the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains. <hi>Nicelius, li.</hi> 3. <hi>de Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perio Alex.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ariepertus,</hi> the Brother of <hi>Theudolinda</hi> created King of the <hi>Lumbards,</hi> when he had raigned nine years, bequeathed the kingdom to <hi>Bertanus,</hi> and <hi>Godopertus</hi> his Sons. The kingdome being divided, <hi>Bertanus</hi> placed his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall leat at <hi>Milan,</hi> and
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:169919:84"/>
                  <hi>Godopertus</hi> at <hi>Ticinum,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (diſſention ſprang be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the two brothers) <hi>Godopertus</hi> ſent to <hi>Grini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daldus</hi> (Duke of <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venta</hi>) a Legate, <hi>Garipal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> Captain, or Duke of <hi>Taureventinus,</hi> to requeſt ſpeedy aide againſt his brother, in recompence whereof he promiſed his kinſwoman in marriage; contrary to which thing the traiterous Legate did perſwade <hi>Grinidaldus</hi> to poſſeſſe the kingdome of <hi>Lembardie,</hi> having now apt time therefore, the brothers being at warres within themſelves; Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Grinivalde</hi> with a
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:169919:84"/>choſen Companie went to <hi>Ticinum,</hi> where being honourablie received (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his marriage, as was thought) into the Kings Palace, did kill <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopertus,</hi> and enjoyed the kingdom. <hi>Bertarius</hi> which was at <hi>Milan</hi> hearing thereof, for fear fled into <hi>Panonia,</hi> or <hi>Hungarie,</hi> to <hi>Cacanus</hi> King of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raries,</hi> a people of <hi>Pano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> leaving behind <hi>Rodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linda</hi> his wife, and <hi>Cami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertus</hi> his Son, whom <hi>Gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivaldus</hi> ſent to <hi>Beneven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venta</hi> not long after, which <hi>Domus Gariopaldus</hi> (the Legate) was in the Temple killed by the
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:169919:85"/>Servant of <hi>Godopertus,</hi> who feared not to be murdered for the revenge of his Maſters injurie. <hi>Bonſinius, li.</hi> 8. <hi>Deca.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Edgarus,</hi> King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> by ſickneſſe loſing the Queen his wife <hi>Elfre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> (on whom he had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>Edward</hi> his Sonne) at what time Fame had blown abroad, that <hi>Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerius,</hi> Duke of <hi>Cornwall,</hi> had a fair Daughter na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Alfreda,</hi> he ſent <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelwold</hi> his familiar com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, as his Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, to ſee the beauty of the Maid, and with his words, and in his name, to demand her in marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:169919:85"/>if her beauty did an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the report. <hi>Ethel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wold</hi> when he had ſeen the beautie of the Maid, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindfull of the Kings commandement, did ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſire to have her for Wife, who returning to the King, ſaid, That ſhe was not ſuch a perſon as was convenient to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpouſed to the King; but a little after, perceiving by this device, that the Kings mind was changed from her love, he began with little, and little, to work with the King to obtain licenſe, that hee might take her by his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; the which (the King
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:169919:86"/>having now deſpiſed her beauty) did eaſily grant. Afterwards the rumour of the beauty of <hi>Alfreda</hi> did more and more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, which moved the King, deſirous to ſee her, to take occaſion to viſit the Town of <hi>Ethelwold</hi> as hee went in hunting. <hi>Ethelwold</hi> when hee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood that the King would come thither, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering the whole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to his wife, prayed her (for the ſafetie of them both.) that ſhe would at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre her ſelfe more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly, and ſhew her ſelfe leſſe beautifull (than ſhee was accuſtomed) to the
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:169919:86"/>young, and luſty King. But the woman forgetting matrimoniall love, and the Children born to <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelwold,</hi> as richly attyred as ſhe could, came forth to meet the King, where (caſting off all ſhame) ſhe gave the occaſion of her Husbands deſtruction, for he was after ſlain, and the King ſhortly married her, of whom he begat many Children. Than which deed nothing did more blemiſh the fame of that worthy King <hi>Edgar,</hi> as well for that hee had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away the Husband, as for that he had eſpouſed the unchaſt Wife. <hi>Polydor,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:169919:87"/>li.</hi> 6. <hi>Ranulphus, li.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. <hi>Will' mus Malmes, li.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 46.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Francis Sabarella</hi> the Cardinall (whoſe writings are highly commended, and allowed, being hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in great authoritie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Civill Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers) ſent Ambaſſadour by <hi>John</hi> the 23. Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> unto the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> to excuſe his fact, and keep him in the Popedome, was au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and occaſion of the Popes utter overthrow, in hope that himſelfe after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards by the conſent of the Councell, ſhould have ſupplied the place of
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:169919:87"/>Pope <hi>John:</hi> But being prevented by death, he at one time did ſatisfie both his Tyrannicall ambition, and unchriſtian treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. <hi>Garmibertus, li.</hi> 5. <hi>de vitis Pontificum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo with one Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie more delivered in Latine, as <hi>Guicchardine</hi> hath written it, I will ſet end to theſe trayterous, and unfaithfull Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours; The which matter I have purpoſely delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in Latine as the courſe of the ſtyle leadeth word for word, and as the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor writ the ſame, for that not reading the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie in any other place,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:169919:88"/>I could not ſo fitly ſet it forth, as mee thinks both ſuch a matter, and the Authors meaning doth require, And yet loth to leave out a thing done in our remembrance, I thought beſt, rather ſo to doe, than utterly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud your Lordſhip ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. The matter is this; <hi>Conſtans fuit multorum o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinio, Albertum Pium Carpenſem, Galliae Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis Lodovici duodecimi apud Julium</hi> 2. <hi>Papam de controverſia inter Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem, &amp; Ferariae Ducem Alfonſum Ateſtinum, &amp; ſalinis Cerine, Comactii orta componenda, Legatum
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:169919:88"/>legationis munere non bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na fide functum, ut Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficem Ferarienſium Ducem contetaret operam dediſſe. Ad id<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ardentiſsimo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderio, in quo ad mortem uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> permanſit impulſum, ut Alfonſus Ferarien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi principatu ſpoliaretur. Quum Hercules Alfonſi pater ante paucos annos à Gilberto Pio dimidiam Carpenſem ditionem acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſſet, ei<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Saxuli caſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum cum nonnullis aliis oppidis permutationem de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſet. Albertus ne tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem (ut ſaepe neceſſe eum minus potentem potentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris vicini cupiditate ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere) ei alteram partem,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:169919:89"/>quae ad ſe ſpectaret, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedere cogeretur, metue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat. Guicchard. li.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>With which Latine Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie concluding, and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering what I have read concerning ſuch unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Legates, who without better government may be drawn into Treaſon, one of the moſt wicked evills, which by their own occaſion, and folly they may raſhly fall into, I will finiſh up the enlarging of this propoſition concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing trayterous Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, with their manner of treacherie. And take upon me briefly in like order, with like manner
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:169919:89"/>of examples to treat of one other miſchiefe that followeth ſuch Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours; For as there is no Body but hath its ſhadow, no Corn but hath its chaffe, no Wine but hath its lees; nor any man that at all times, in all places, in all matters, and to all perſons doth ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe alike perfect wiſe: So ſince theſe Legates hereafter may (as before time they have) by words, by writings, by deeds, by geſtures, ſhew ſome folly in them (though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe perhaps not to bee diſcommended) I will now diſcourſe of fooliſh
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:169919:90"/>Ambaſſadours to give light to others, and to ſave them out of ſuch condemned actions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 11. <hi>Of the fooliſh ſayings, and doings of Ambaſſadours.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOtwithſtanding that it often happeneth to be counted a point of wiſdome to diſſemble, and to utter great folly, yet in a Legate, in a matter of gravitie, in the benefit of a Countrie, in the cauſe of a King, to ſhew either folly in the tongue, raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:169919:90"/>in the hand, light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the geſture, clow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhneſs in action, or want of good government in ordering himſelfe, is not ſimply a fault in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, which yet is not to bee allowed, but alſo it ſtretcheth further, and miniſtreth occaſion to condemn the Maſter, or Prince, for want of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that either hee had not people out of whom, or elſe had not in him to diſcern to whom he might have better committed ſuch a waighty charge, a thing not to be imagined of the head, and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:169919:91"/>and kingdome; Wherefore as you have before on the one ſide wiſe Ambaſſadours, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured and commended for their ſingular and quick wits in anſwering, for their worthy, and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent diſpatch of their Embaſſie in action. So on the other ſide you ſhall now ſee, That they who doe not adviſedly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the place wherein, the perſon to whom, the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter whereof they are to uſe their ſpeech, doe not only fall into many groſſe errors, which hurt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, in jurie their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and ſhame their
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:169919:91"/>Princes; But that they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo thereby become a note, and blot of Ignominie to be left behind them in their utter condemnation, and the heavy reproch of their poſteritie, as is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by theſe perſons fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, vouched for that intent, whoſe children al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they might be condemned, as diſcended from Ambaſſadours, yet it is reprochfull to have the folly, and evill of their Anceſtors to be ſpightful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly objected unto them. And ſo to the matter. The people of <hi>Florence</hi> ſent an Orator or Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour to <hi>Jane</hi> Queen of
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:169919:92"/>
                  <hi>Naples</hi> (of life inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, and ſuch a perſon as hanged her Husband, a gallant young Prince, out of her Chamber window, for that he could not the night before content her immoderate, and inſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble leacherie) called <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis,</hi> a certain Lawyer by profeſſion, but better lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in wearing the appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell of a Civillian, than deeply ſeen in the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Juſtinian;</hi> And yet more unlearned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed then he appeared in ſhew. This man being called into the Queens preſence to performe his charge; when he had ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:169919:92"/>with ſome good care the effects of his Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, was the next day commanded to return to the Court to hear his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: (In the mean time having intelligence, that the Queen loved proper men, not diſdaining ſuch perſons as were of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent beauty) but when ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he was returned to Court, there after many things ſpoken this way, and that way, about his Embaſſie unto the Queen, at length more impudent than wiſe, more glorious than ſeemly, brake with the Queen, and ſaid, that
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:169919:93"/>he had farre more ſecret matters to impart unto her. Whereupon the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Queen deſirous to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie his Legation in all convenient order, and deeming the matters of great importance ſhould be revealed unto her ſelf, courteouſly called him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a more ſecret place, where the fool, beſides all order, and civilitie, much flattering himſelfe in the excellencie of his beautie, demanded of her ſocietie in the act of <hi>Venus.</hi> At which the wiſe Queen no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing abaſhed, nor altered into any ſudden paſſion, beholding the counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:169919:93"/>of the man, did on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſmiling ask whether the Florentines had given him the ſame in commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on alſo, and telling him that he were beſt to have authority therefore, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out further anger willed him to depart home. <hi>Pog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius in facetiis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ariſton</hi> the Tyrant of <hi>Athens,</hi> (beſieged and ſubdued by <hi>L. Sylla,</hi> and being in great povertie, and want of all things) did ſend two Legates, or Meſſengers into the Camp to <hi>Sylla</hi> (but they with the minds of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, and not with an humble, or gentle ſtile ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:169919:94"/>to the preſent for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune beginning with the praiſe of <hi>Theſeus,</hi> and <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſuenta,</hi> together with the memorie of things done againſt the Medes, and other Nations by the Athenians, did gloriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and fooliſhly execute their Legation, by which they did not only not mitigate the mind of the enemy, but made him far more offended than hee was before, ſaying that they were a people moſt happy, and therefore meete to carry back ſuch praiſes again, for hee was ſent to <hi>Athens</hi> by the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Rome,</hi> not to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:169919:94"/>in learning, but utterly to overthrow the taken City of <hi>Athens,</hi> which he did after per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme. <hi>Sab. li.</hi> 9. <hi>en.</hi> 6. <hi>ex Plut. Sylla.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Peruſines ſending Orators to <hi>Urbaim</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> (afflicted with ſickneſſe) one of them without reſpect of the griefe of the Pope, uſed a long, and tedious Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The other who grieved at the folly of the firſt Speaker, then being to mend all, fell into a far more offence to move an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in the Biſhop, ſaying, That it was given them in charge, that except they
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:169919:95"/>were anſwered forthwith, they ſhould repeat the ſame Oration again. At whoſe folly the Biſhop ſmiling, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded them to be quickly diſpatched. <hi>Poggius in facetiis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Franciſcus Codelmerius</hi> a Cardinall, being with a Navy ſent Legate againſt the Turks, ſubduing <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſpont,</hi> by his folly, and ignorance, ſuffered the Turks to paſſe out of that ſtreight, and gave no war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the Chriſtians, wherein he might, and did ſeem to be author (by his ſtupiditie) of that me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable, and lamentable ſlaughter of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:169919:95"/>at <hi>Varua. Garimber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, li.</hi> 6. <hi>De vitis Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the wars which were kept between Pope <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie</hi> the Eleventh, and the Florentines, a Legate of the Racavatenſes being ſent to <hi>Florence,</hi> gave them thanks for the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties reſtored, inveighing with many deſpightfull words againſt the Biſhop, and the Princes of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, &amp; the Miniſters of the Biſhop, having no reſpect to <hi>Radolphus,</hi> Lord of the Camerines, who was then <hi>Potimanſis</hi> or chiefe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>Florence,</hi> for the Biſhop. Whereupon
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:169919:96"/>
                  <hi>Radolphus</hi> demanded of the Ambaſſadour of what facultie or Art he was, to whom he anſwered, a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of the Civill Law, then he asked how long he had applied that ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, the Legate ſaid, more than ten years. O reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Radolphus,</hi> very glad would I have been, that you had beſtowed a yeare thereof to learn diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and wiſdome, judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him a ſimple foole, that in his preſence being one of the number, would ſo laviſhly bluſter out ſuch heavie words againſt the Princes and Rulers. <hi>Poggius.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="173" facs="tcp:169919:96"/>
               <p>The Venetians diſpat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched two young Legates to <hi>Frederick</hi> the third Emperour, who being highly offended with their young yeares, forbade them to approach his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, yet at the length they obtained this favour, that they were privatly, and without the order of the Cuſtome of Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours (which openly ſhould deliver their Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage) brought to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, at what time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all humanitie, or wiſdome, out of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter propounded, they ſaid that if all wiſdome and learning reſted in a beard,
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:169919:97"/>and in white haires, the Senate of <hi>Venice</hi> had in place of them, to ſend to the Emperour two faire <hi>Barbara</hi> Goates, with which proud anſwer, they confirmed the ſuſpition this Emperour conceived of their folly. <hi>Aegidius Cororetus de dictis, &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis memor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here winding up the Clue of my raw thred, ſpun, and woven to make the mournfull garment for unfit Ambaſſadours to wear, that is, to cloth them with reproch to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie, for that they were fooliſh, Traytors, proud, diſdainfull, unfit for ſo
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:169919:97"/>honourable a place, I will only now adde to this matter one title more, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a badge of their office, and ſo ſet end to this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly diſcourſe of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters belonging to Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours, for both ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of time, and tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of the matter, and indigeſtion in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, doe will mee with ſpeed (remembring <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> divine Speech, That <hi>in multiloquio non deeſt peccatum</hi>) to draw to my journeys end, leſt my weary hand, and my ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Pen, thinking to reach to a further place, doe
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:169919:98"/>break their wind, and caſt their Maſter into the myre, whoſe end is then farre worſe than his haſtie beginning. And thus to the laſt title.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 12. <hi>Of Perſons ſent divers times in Embaſſie.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS the end for every thing maketh the ſame happy, or evill, as the Proverb is, <hi>Bonus exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus omnia probat,</hi> ſo of a good beginning by grace,
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:169919:98"/>continued for vertue, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted with order, exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by good mindes, performed of neceſſitie, there muſt enſue a good end, no leſſe worthy ſuch a beginning; For as the good life is cauſe of a good and quiet death; So the milde, and godly death, declare the former good life of the Perſon; And therefore ſince my beginning by intent was good; the continuance for matter not unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, for order not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether confuſed, and for the commoditie that may enſue not to bee rejected
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:169919:99"/>(ſince this benefit com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth thereby, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it bee not worthy the reading of your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and although it bring no great learning to others, yet to mee who travell my wit and hand, my ſtudie and pen there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, it bringeth advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage) I hope a good end, and concluſion of matter will follow; For as the beginning of this 'Treatiſe was in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of the wiſe, learned, and worthy Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours; So with like end in praiſe of them, and their travell, I will
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:169919:99"/>finiſh this ſimple Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe; And for that there is nothing can beautifie their perſon, increaſe their honour, augment their ſubſtance, win love of their Countrie, gain credit amongſt ſtrangers, favour of their Prince, and friendſhip amongſt all men, than oftentimes to ſupply the place of ſo weightie, and honourable a charge; Therefore I will ſay ſomewhat of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers perſons, who divers times, to divers Princes, and in divers matters have won ſingular com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations therefore,
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:169919:100"/>committing all other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to ſilence, which I could ſpeak of them, and their office; Since theſe Meſſengers of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to Princes, had their firſt originall from the Angellicall Order of Archangells, who are made the Ambaſſadours of God, to great Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages in great matters, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Revelation of the ſucceſſe of Kingdomes, as <hi>Gabriel</hi> was to <hi>Daniel,</hi> or of opening ſome rare, and ſtrange thing, as hee was alſo to the Virgin of the Conception of the Saviour of our Souls,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:169919:100"/>and Redeemer of us from our Sinnes; For this is certain, that there is no order, or government in this world, as well Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall as Temporall, but it is had from the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of the Celeſtiall Hierarchie; Since God Created the world, and appointed the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof according to the Architype, chiefe pattern, or Ideall forme of the ſame, conceived in the divine mind, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in the Celeſtiall Hierarchy. But enough of this, and perchance to ſome cavelling heads,
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:169919:101"/>(who as yet have not taſted the ſweet kernell of the hard Nut) too much to bee diſcovered. And ſo once again to my Ambaſſadours which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers times have enjoyed that Function, whereof I (although I might produce many good, and preſent examples) both of our own Countrie, in our own remembrance, and living in our preſent dayes, As of your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, of whom for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty I will forbear to ſpeak, who have now twice been Ambaſſadour, And of Maſter Doctor
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:169919:101"/>
                  <hi>Nicholas Wootton,</hi> who being Counſellour to four Princes, was alſo divers times Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, of Sir <hi>Johu Maſon</hi> likewiſe, and many other our Countrie-men: yet I will only here powre out of the ſmall ſtore of my Collections, ſuch as in times paſt in forraign Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have enjoyed ſuch high and honourable title.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caius Lelius,</hi> Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour to <hi>Africa</hi> going into <hi>Spain,</hi> was Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in the expugnation of New <hi>Carthage,</hi> as <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie</hi> witneſſeth, who alſo
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:169919:102"/>being ſent Ambaſſadour from <hi>Scipio</hi> to <hi>Syphaces</hi> for concluſion of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, did lead with him certain Tribunes expert in the feats of Arms, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the form of Servants, to the intent to deſcrie the manner of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, as writeth <hi>Frontinus;</hi> in which Legation hee wiſely wrought that <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaces</hi> became friend to the Romans. <hi>Volat. li.</hi> 16. <hi>Urb. Com.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gidius Carilla</hi> was ſent from <hi>Innocent</hi> the ſixth high Biſhop to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the matters of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly,</hi> who being by birth
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:169919:102"/>a Spaniard, of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Carilla,</hi> was ſo ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular wiſe in the deſpatch of his affaires in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Biſhop, that he pacified the State of the Church at that time miſerably vexed with many, and great tumults, which man alſo of <hi>Urban</hi> the ſixth, being again ſent into <hi>Italy,</hi> brought under the obedience of Count <hi>Barnabas,</hi> moleſting the quiet of the Biſhop; who likewiſe before of <hi>Urban</hi> the Fifth, was ſent Legate into <hi>Italy. Volat. li.</hi> 22. <hi>Anthropo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quintus Cicero,</hi> the
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:169919:103"/>brother of <hi>Marcus Tullius Cicero,</hi> the Legate of <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> was the chiefe in 14. Embaſſies, <hi>Volat.</hi> 29.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Epiphanius</hi> the moſt holy Biſhop did execute the office of many Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations for <hi>Theodericus</hi> King of the Goths, and for many others, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes returned moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, in that every thing in thoſe ſeverall cauſes ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded well according to his mind. <hi>Ennodius in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus vita.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo concluding this Title of ſuch perſons as have divers times ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:169919:103"/>the office of an Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador with the number of foure Forraigne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples (thinking the ſame number in Arithmetick to poſſeſſe vertue) As all the Divines, both La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, Greeks, and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews, aſwell Cabaliſts as others doe fully agree, and not without great reaſon moſt learnedly and Chriſtianly do main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain againſt unlearned and fooliſh opinions of ſuch as doe groſsly judge ſuch hidden myſteries of numbers to be ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, contrary to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which voucheth that
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:169919:104"/>God made the world, in waight, number, and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, which three doe ſignifie Muſick, Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metique and Geometry, of which number of Four, I referre the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to another more convenient time. I will in few words ſet end un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this my unorderly, but well meaning Diſcourſe of Ambaſſadours in a ſhort Epilogue by way of recapitulation knitting up the ſumme of all that which before in thoſe Examples have been ſo hudled up together in hotch-poch.</p>
               <pb n="189" facs="tcp:169919:104"/>
               <p>Wherefore firſt it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth that. Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours having their exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from Heaven, and their originall upon earth, were uſed in all Ages, in all matters, amongſt all men of ſundrie Nations, of the Jewes, Gentiles, Greeks, Barbarians, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, and other people.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that he who in honour ſhould furniſh the place of ſuch a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, muſt be free born, no bond man, ſtout, and valiant, not daſtard-like, or a coward, that he muſt be learned, not ignorant, wiſe, not fooliſh, quick
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:169919:105"/>of wit, not blockiſh and dull, faithfull, no traytor, that he muſt be rewarded, not ſuffered to conſume his ſubſtance. That hee muſt in his Embaſſie bee well intreated, not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed, murthered, or have any villanie, or injury permitted to be done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and that hee muſt be of good calling, and eſtimation in his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie before hee be ſent, not a Crafts-man, a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving-man, a common Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen, a mean Prieſt, an Advocate, or a defamed perſon, either for Perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, Simonie, Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:169919:105"/>or any other kind of evill life. For if he be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furniſhed with theſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and garniſhed with theſe vices, hee is not only not worthy to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the place of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſie in a Forraign Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, where hee ſhall doe his Countrie good, his Prince honour, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe good, and credit; But hee rather well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth as a wicked, and hatefull perſon to be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed into ſome other Countrie, there to rid his Common-wealth of ſuch an evill member, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come opprobrious to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:169919:106"/>Nations, and in all places of the world to receive due puniſhment for his evill deſervings.</p>
               <p>Thus having ended my Chriſtmaſſe work done in the middeſt of my Chriſtmaſſe plaies, as may appear by the Chriſtmaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly handling thereof, I after Chriſtmaſſe conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate the ſame to your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable acceptance, not as a thing worthy your deſert and judgement, but as a thing that anſwereth my deſire, and good meaning. The which I beſeech your Lordſhip to accept as lovingly from
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:169919:106"/>mee, as it is preſented willingly by mee unto you, with whom (as ſoon as by leaſure I might, and as by learning I was able, and as a body born out of time, but yet thinking it better late than never) I deemed it my dutie to congratulate your return with ſome ſuch poor gift, as the Reliques of my ſpoyled Librarie in the time of mine impove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing, and infortunate trouble, would yield mee abilitie to beſtow.</p>
               <p>And thus moſt humbly commending me to your
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:169919:107"/>Honourable liking, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting you to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighties protection, I dutifully take my leave this eighth of <hi>Januarie</hi> 1578. at <hi>Longleate</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:169919:107"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
